<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-16T17:24:56+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Will Ranjan-Churchill</title><subtitle>Just a guy, standing in front of the vast array of tech available to small to mid-sized organisations, trying to make sense of the world.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On tech for tech’s sake</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/on-tech-for-techs-sake/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On tech for tech’s sake" /><published>2025-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/on-tech-for-techs-sake</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/on-tech-for-techs-sake/"><![CDATA[<p>You may well know that <a href="https://buttondown.com/willrc">I have a newsletter</a>.</p>

<p>My reasoning was simple: I spend a lot of my time reading tech news, so why not share my thoughts on it? I already use <a href="https://readwise.io/">Readwise</a> (RIP Omnivore) to make notes on things I read, so surely it would only be a little effort to turn that into useful content for others.</p>

<p>Having had the thought, some hours later I had the perfect system. Using an automation platform and the OpenAI API, I had a completely automated workflow that, once a week, took all my notes from tech articles I’d read in the past 7 days, structured them into an email, generated an intro and outro for the whole thing, and then sent that to me so that it could make final edits before sending it to my adoring fans.</p>

<p>There was just one problem.</p>

<p>It sucked.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://willrc.co.uk/content/images/Overengineering-a-Newsletter-1.png" alt="" class="post-image post-image-wide" style="" />
  <figcaption class="post-image-caption"></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The system itself worked flawlessly. And if I’d wanted an AI generated round-up of the things I’d read that week, this would have been fine. Perfect, in fact. But I used the system for about a month, and there wasn’t a single thing the AI wrote for me that I didn’t rewrite into my own words.</p>

<p>Yes, I could refine the AI Assistant, feed it examples of my writing, and make it better at mimicing me. But the thing is, I <em>like</em> writing the newsletter. What’s more, I don’t want people to read AI-generated thoughts on articles that <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/torconstantino/2024/08/26/is-ai-quietly-killing-itself-and-the-internet/?ss=ai">apparently have a 50/50 shot</a> of being, themselves, AI-generated.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There wasn’t a single thing the AI wrote that I didn’t end up rewriting.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When you take that bit out, all the automation is really doing is sending the content through half a dozen different systems to wrangle it into a format that will play nice with the next system in the chain. Aside from that not really making sense, it’s terrible practice. If any one of those services changes the way they work, it could break my entire flow.</p>

<p>Here’s what I do now:</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://willrc.co.uk/content/images/Not-Overengineering-a-Newsletter-3.png" alt="" class="post-image post-image-wide" style="" />
  <figcaption class="post-image-caption"></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Notice anything? It’s basically the exact same thing I was doing, without the automation block. I’m doing, essentially, exactly the same amount of work with or without the automation.</p>

<h2 id="the-human-desire-to-over-use-technology">The human desire to over-use technology</h2>

<p>Don’t get me wrong. There are plenty of things that automation is good for. And being able to use ChatGPT and others to assist with some of life’s more mundane office tasks is great.</p>

<p>But just because these technologies exist, it doesn’t mean we <strong>have</strong> to use them. For me and my newsletter, there isn’t really any benefit for me in overengineering a solution. Cramming new and shiny technology into places where there is no need for it just doesn’t make sense. And that’s before you start to think about the moral and ethical implications of some of the technology we use.</p>

<p>There’s often a real fear that if we aren’t at least dabbling the latest and greatest, we’ll fall behind to the point of obselecence. So let me be one voice on the other side of that argument. <strong>It’s ok to not always be at the bleeding edge.</strong></p>

<p>I’m not saying stick your head in the sand - there’s a balance. Be aware of the landscape and what’s going on, and then judge for yourselves (with some <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/contact/">professional help</a> if needed…) what the right tools for the job are.</p>

<p>But if you’re looking at a new tool that someone is selling you, and you can’t figure out where it makes sense to put it in your organisation, there’s a good chance that’s because it doesn’t fit. And that’s ok.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong><em>Want to read the</em></strong> <strong><em>newsletter in question? Pop your email in the box below. You can also catch up on past issues <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/newsletter/">here</a>.</em></strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinions" /><category term="ai" /><category term="chatgpt" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You may well know that I have a newsletter. My reasoning was simple: I spend a lot of my time reading tech news, so why not share my thoughts on it? I already use Readwise (RIP Omnivore) to make notes on things I read, so surely it would only be a little effort to turn that into useful content for others. Having had the thought, some hours later I had the perfect system. Using an automation platform and the OpenAI API, I had a completely automated workflow that, once a week, took all my notes from tech articles I’d read in the past 7 days, structured them into an email, generated an intro and outro for the whole thing, and then sent that to me so that it could make final edits before sending it to my adoring fans. There was just one problem. It sucked. The system itself worked flawlessly. And if I’d wanted an AI generated round-up of the things I’d read that week, this would have been fine. Perfect, in fact. But I used the system for about a month, and there wasn’t a single thing the AI wrote for me that I didn’t rewrite into my own words. Yes, I could refine the AI Assistant, feed it examples of my writing, and make it better at mimicing me. But the thing is, I like writing the newsletter. What’s more, I don’t want people to read AI-generated thoughts on articles that apparently have a 50/50 shot of being, themselves, AI-generated. There wasn’t a single thing the AI wrote that I didn’t end up rewriting. When you take that bit out, all the automation is really doing is sending the content through half a dozen different systems to wrangle it into a format that will play nice with the next system in the chain. Aside from that not really making sense, it’s terrible practice. If any one of those services changes the way they work, it could break my entire flow. Here’s what I do now: Notice anything? It’s basically the exact same thing I was doing, without the automation block. I’m doing, essentially, exactly the same amount of work with or without the automation. The human desire to over-use technology Don’t get me wrong. There are plenty of things that automation is good for. And being able to use ChatGPT and others to assist with some of life’s more mundane office tasks is great. But just because these technologies exist, it doesn’t mean we have to use them. For me and my newsletter, there isn’t really any benefit for me in overengineering a solution. Cramming new and shiny technology into places where there is no need for it just doesn’t make sense. And that’s before you start to think about the moral and ethical implications of some of the technology we use. There’s often a real fear that if we aren’t at least dabbling the latest and greatest, we’ll fall behind to the point of obselecence. So let me be one voice on the other side of that argument. It’s ok to not always be at the bleeding edge. I’m not saying stick your head in the sand - there’s a balance. Be aware of the landscape and what’s going on, and then judge for yourselves (with some professional help if needed…) what the right tools for the job are. But if you’re looking at a new tool that someone is selling you, and you can’t figure out where it makes sense to put it in your organisation, there’s a good chance that’s because it doesn’t fit. And that’s ok. Want to read the newsletter in question? Pop your email in the box below. You can also catch up on past issues here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Pile-of-Tech.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Pile-of-Tech.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting hacked - its not “if”, it’s “when”</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/getting-hacked-its-not-if-its-when/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting hacked - its not “if”, it’s “when”" /><published>2024-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/getting-hacked-its-not-if-its-when</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/getting-hacked-its-not-if-its-when/"><![CDATA[<p>I spend much of my professional time reminding people of the importance of good cyber security. This week, that lesson hit home for me, as my LinkedIn profile was hacked. For about 48 hours someone else had complete control over my account.</p>

<p>And they really did a number on me. For starters, they changed my password and changed the two-step verification to make sure I couldn’t get back in. They also changed my name and profile picture, replaced all my education and work experience, and deleted all my recent activity to replace it with their own.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://willrc.co.uk/content/images/1000070597-460x1024.png" alt="image alt here" class="post-image " style="" />
  <figcaption class="post-image-caption">I had a fun couple of days going back and forth with LinkedIn... Thanks "Lesley".</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It could have been worse. I eventually got it back (by filling out <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/help/linkedin/answer/a1340402">LinkedIn’s Report Unauthorized Access form</a>). In any case, there are limited (though not zero) things you can do with access to my LinkedIn account. The whole experience did serve as a reminder that, even if you’re constantly preaching the good cyber security word, no one is immune from being compromised.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s not a case of “if” you get hacked, but “when”.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m still looking in to how it happened, but it could have been a number of different things. My current working theory is that I fell foul of any one of a number of recent <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/news/story/nearly-10-billion-passwords-leaked-6091644/">password leaks</a>. Or maybe it isn’t as complicated as that. LinkedIn is not exactly known for being Fort Knox. <a href="https://nazmul-ahsan.medium.com/your-linkedin-account-can-get-hacked-by-anyone-and-there-is-nothing-you-can-do-about-it-2fbf17a6ddd4">This blog post</a> from LinkedIn user Nazmul Ahsan, describes how all it took to lose his account was for someone to contact customer service and pretend to be him.</p>

<p>But why would anyone bother? I’m not particularly active on LinkedIn, and there isn’t much data held privately that you can’t see on my public profile. What benefit does someone get by stealing my account?</p>

<p>Well, in 2024 it’s getting increasingly harder to scam people. As viewers of Netflix’s Sweet Bobby will know, one of the things that makes a lie believable is accompanying evidence. Creating a series of fake social media accounts is easy. Creating <em>believable</em> social media accounts, with hundreds of connections to other people? Well, that’s a little more complicated. It’s far easier to just steal an existing account, wipe the recent history, and replace it with your own content. I suspect that, if I’d let the perpetrator carry on, they would have used it as a base from which to scam other people.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everyone is <strong>a</strong> target, even if you’re not <strong>the</strong> target.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="how-can-you-protect-yourself-against-hackers">How can you protect yourself against hackers?</h2>

<p>I’ve already said that being hacked is inevitable, and I stand by that. But that doesn’t mean you shouldn’t still put up a good fight. What can you do to make it as hard as possible for people to get access to your data?</p>

<h3 id="good-password-hygiene-is-crucial">Good password hygiene is crucial.</h3>

<p>This section should be teaching you to suck eggs. But I would be remiss as a technology professional if I didn’t put it here, so let’s just dive in.</p>

<h4 id="make-your-passwords-long-and-complicated"><strong>Make your passwords long and complicated.</strong></h4>

<p>A simple piece of advice for a simple reason. Regardless of whether a human or a machine is trying to guess your password, the longer and more complicated it is, the harder it will be to guess. Adding symbols, numbers, and a mixture of upper and lower case letters all add to the complexity.</p>

<p>Hard to guess doesn’t have to be hard to remember. BeCyberSafe.com have an excellent article for <a href="https://www.becybersafe.com/passwords/password-ideas.html">12 Strong Password Ideas</a>, one of which is using a sentence as your password. For example, rather than putting your cat’s name followed by “1234”, you might have a password like “MittensReallyLikesHer3SquareMealsADay!”. It includes the usually compulsory mixture of cases, numbers, and special characters, while also being long and hard to guess.</p>

<h4 id="dont-use-the-same-password-for-multiple-accounts"><strong>Don’t use the same password for multiple accounts.</strong></h4>

<p>If I used the same password for LinkedIn as, say, for my email account, then anyone gaining access to one also gets the other. If you control my email account, you have a much stronger chance of being able to gain access to pretty much any online service I have - including the big scary ones like online banking, government portals, etc.</p>

<p>By making sure that every single account I have uses a different password, I limit my exposure if one of those accounts is compromised.</p>

<h4 id="change-your-password-frequently"><strong>Change your password frequently.</strong></h4>

<p>This advice is not as universal as the others. In fact, even the National Cyber Security Centre recommends <a href="https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/blog-post/problems-forcing-regular-password-expiry">not forcing users to frequently change passwords</a>. There is good reason for that. If you’re asking people to change their passwords every 3 months, eventually they are going to get bored of thinking up new complex passwords. Instead, they’ll settle for the old “stick an exclamation mark at the end of the last password” method. This is a slippery slope to weaker and weaker passwords, until you’re all but forced by your brain to just use the same simple password for everything, because you can’t think of your 43rd new password of the year for yet another platform.</p>

<p>On the flipside, if your data gets leaked, by changing your passwords frequently you limit the amount of time between your password being available and it being useful. Legally, organisations who know of a data leak should report this to users as soon as possible. So you could just keep an eye out… on every communication channel… for every online service you use… assuming that every platform knows the second they are breached… and are definitely not slow to let everyone know about it…</p>

<p>All I’m saying is that while I agree with the NCSC that forcing people to change their passwords frequently can lead to lazy passwords, it can give an extra layer of protection. <strong><em>But only if your passwords are good.</em></strong> And to make sure you hit all of these criteria, we move onto the next tool in your arsenal…</p>

<h3 id="if-all-this-sounds-like-a-lot-have-you-considered-a-password-manager">If all this sounds like a lot, have you considered a password manager?</h3>

<p>I literally can’t count the number of online services I use. The idea that I could come up with a complex, unique password for each of those, and change it even once a year (let alone every 3 months), is madness. So I don’t bother with any of that.</p>

<p>Instead, I use a password manager. There are loads of options: LastPass, Bitwarden, 1Password, Proton Pass, to name just 4 off the top of my head. Each has their own set of pros and cons, their own price points, and their own loyal user bases. Which one is right for you will depend, but look out for some basic protections like strong encryption, secure password generators, and helpful bonuses like dark web scanning.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Need help finding the right password manager for you? <a href="https://calendly.com/willrc/free-consultation">Let’s have a chat!</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>“But Will? What if the Password Manager gets hacked?”</strong> I hear you ask. What a fantastic question. And it does happen. A couple of years ago LastPass - a service I often recommended - <a href="https://blog.lastpass.com/posts/notice-of-recent-security-incident">suffered a major data breach</a>. This is where ensuring your password manager has strong encryption comes in. In the LastPass case, hackers gained access to a bunch of passwords, but they couldn’t read them without breaking the encryption. This is <em>technically</em> possible, but extremely hard to do.</p>

<p>But nothing is flawless, and that’s why you need one more string to your cyber security bow…</p>

<h3 id="dont-just-rely-on-your-password">Don’t just rely on your password.</h3>

<p>Use Multifactor Authentication wherever possible. Sometimes called 2-Factor Authentication, or Two Step Verification, this is exactly what it sounds like. Your password is not the only thing the platform will ask you for to ensure you are the owner of the account.</p>

<p>Most major platforms will allow you to do this now, and some (including most banks) in fact demand it. It is annoying, I know. It’s annoying to setup. And it’s annoying having to dig out your phone every time you want to check your Bluesky feed on your laptop. But take it from me, having to spend the day undoing a bunch of changes to your compromised LinkedIn account - including adding back in nearly 20 years of deleted work experience - is considerably more annoying.</p>

<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts…</h2>

<p>You might be thinking that, as a technology consultant (and general IT-know-it-all), I would be pretty embarrassed that I lost control of my LinkedIn account for two days.</p>

<p>But the truth is I’m not.</p>

<p>Everyone, at some point in their online journey, is going to experience a cyber security mishap. Maybe it will be a dodgy email you don’t quite read properly, a link you don’t double check. Perhaps, you really needed to send a work email and the only option was public WiFi. Or, maybe you did everything right, and an online service suffers a data breach.</p>

<p>Whatever the reason, if it hasn’t happened to you yet, it will. Don’t panic, and don’t be ashamed. Just don’t make it too easy.</p>

<p><em>If you want to chat about any cyber security worries you have, why not book a <a href="https://calendly.com/willrc/free-consultation">free 20 minute call</a> with me?</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="guides" /><category term="communication" /><category term="cyber-security" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I spend much of my professional time reminding people of the importance of good cyber security. This week, that lesson hit home for me, as my LinkedIn profile was hacked. For about 48 hours someone else had complete control over my account. And they really did a number on me. For starters, they changed my password and changed the two-step verification to make sure I couldn’t get back in. They also changed my name and profile picture, replaced all my education and work experience, and deleted all my recent activity to replace it with their own. I had a fun couple of days going back and forth with LinkedIn... Thanks "Lesley". It could have been worse. I eventually got it back (by filling out LinkedIn’s Report Unauthorized Access form). In any case, there are limited (though not zero) things you can do with access to my LinkedIn account. The whole experience did serve as a reminder that, even if you’re constantly preaching the good cyber security word, no one is immune from being compromised. It’s not a case of “if” you get hacked, but “when”. I’m still looking in to how it happened, but it could have been a number of different things. My current working theory is that I fell foul of any one of a number of recent password leaks. Or maybe it isn’t as complicated as that. LinkedIn is not exactly known for being Fort Knox. This blog post from LinkedIn user Nazmul Ahsan, describes how all it took to lose his account was for someone to contact customer service and pretend to be him. But why would anyone bother? I’m not particularly active on LinkedIn, and there isn’t much data held privately that you can’t see on my public profile. What benefit does someone get by stealing my account? Well, in 2024 it’s getting increasingly harder to scam people. As viewers of Netflix’s Sweet Bobby will know, one of the things that makes a lie believable is accompanying evidence. Creating a series of fake social media accounts is easy. Creating believable social media accounts, with hundreds of connections to other people? Well, that’s a little more complicated. It’s far easier to just steal an existing account, wipe the recent history, and replace it with your own content. I suspect that, if I’d let the perpetrator carry on, they would have used it as a base from which to scam other people. Everyone is a target, even if you’re not the target. How can you protect yourself against hackers? I’ve already said that being hacked is inevitable, and I stand by that. But that doesn’t mean you shouldn’t still put up a good fight. What can you do to make it as hard as possible for people to get access to your data? Good password hygiene is crucial. This section should be teaching you to suck eggs. But I would be remiss as a technology professional if I didn’t put it here, so let’s just dive in. Make your passwords long and complicated. A simple piece of advice for a simple reason. Regardless of whether a human or a machine is trying to guess your password, the longer and more complicated it is, the harder it will be to guess. Adding symbols, numbers, and a mixture of upper and lower case letters all add to the complexity. Hard to guess doesn’t have to be hard to remember. BeCyberSafe.com have an excellent article for 12 Strong Password Ideas, one of which is using a sentence as your password. For example, rather than putting your cat’s name followed by “1234”, you might have a password like “MittensReallyLikesHer3SquareMealsADay!”. It includes the usually compulsory mixture of cases, numbers, and special characters, while also being long and hard to guess. Don’t use the same password for multiple accounts. If I used the same password for LinkedIn as, say, for my email account, then anyone gaining access to one also gets the other. If you control my email account, you have a much stronger chance of being able to gain access to pretty much any online service I have - including the big scary ones like online banking, government portals, etc. By making sure that every single account I have uses a different password, I limit my exposure if one of those accounts is compromised. Change your password frequently. This advice is not as universal as the others. In fact, even the National Cyber Security Centre recommends not forcing users to frequently change passwords. There is good reason for that. If you’re asking people to change their passwords every 3 months, eventually they are going to get bored of thinking up new complex passwords. Instead, they’ll settle for the old “stick an exclamation mark at the end of the last password” method. This is a slippery slope to weaker and weaker passwords, until you’re all but forced by your brain to just use the same simple password for everything, because you can’t think of your 43rd new password of the year for yet another platform. On the flipside, if your data gets leaked, by changing your passwords frequently you limit the amount of time between your password being available and it being useful. Legally, organisations who know of a data leak should report this to users as soon as possible. So you could just keep an eye out… on every communication channel… for every online service you use… assuming that every platform knows the second they are breached… and are definitely not slow to let everyone know about it… All I’m saying is that while I agree with the NCSC that forcing people to change their passwords frequently can lead to lazy passwords, it can give an extra layer of protection. But only if your passwords are good. And to make sure you hit all of these criteria, we move onto the next tool in your arsenal… If all this sounds like a lot, have you considered a password manager? I literally can’t count the number of online services I use. The idea that I could come up with a complex, unique password for each of those, and change it even once a year (let alone every 3 months), is madness. So I don’t bother with any of that. Instead, I use a password manager. There are loads of options: LastPass, Bitwarden, 1Password, Proton Pass, to name just 4 off the top of my head. Each has their own set of pros and cons, their own price points, and their own loyal user bases. Which one is right for you will depend, but look out for some basic protections like strong encryption, secure password generators, and helpful bonuses like dark web scanning. Need help finding the right password manager for you? Let’s have a chat! “But Will? What if the Password Manager gets hacked?” I hear you ask. What a fantastic question. And it does happen. A couple of years ago LastPass - a service I often recommended - suffered a major data breach. This is where ensuring your password manager has strong encryption comes in. In the LastPass case, hackers gained access to a bunch of passwords, but they couldn’t read them without breaking the encryption. This is technically possible, but extremely hard to do. But nothing is flawless, and that’s why you need one more string to your cyber security bow… Don’t just rely on your password. Use Multifactor Authentication wherever possible. Sometimes called 2-Factor Authentication, or Two Step Verification, this is exactly what it sounds like. Your password is not the only thing the platform will ask you for to ensure you are the owner of the account. Most major platforms will allow you to do this now, and some (including most banks) in fact demand it. It is annoying, I know. It’s annoying to setup. And it’s annoying having to dig out your phone every time you want to check your Bluesky feed on your laptop. But take it from me, having to spend the day undoing a bunch of changes to your compromised LinkedIn account - including adding back in nearly 20 years of deleted work experience - is considerably more annoying. Final thoughts… You might be thinking that, as a technology consultant (and general IT-know-it-all), I would be pretty embarrassed that I lost control of my LinkedIn account for two days. But the truth is I’m not. Everyone, at some point in their online journey, is going to experience a cyber security mishap. Maybe it will be a dodgy email you don’t quite read properly, a link you don’t double check. Perhaps, you really needed to send a work email and the only option was public WiFi. Or, maybe you did everything right, and an online service suffers a data breach. Whatever the reason, if it hasn’t happened to you yet, it will. Don’t panic, and don’t be ashamed. Just don’t make it too easy. If you want to chat about any cyber security worries you have, why not book a free 20 minute call with me?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/ariel-Oal07Ai4oTk-unsplash.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/ariel-Oal07Ai4oTk-unsplash.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Free and Open Source Software - a crash course</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/free-and-open-source-software-a-crash-course/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free and Open Source Software - a crash course" /><published>2024-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/free-and-open-source-software-a-crash-course</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/free-and-open-source-software-a-crash-course/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="intro---what-is-foss">Intro - what is FOSS?</h1>

<p>Free and Open Source Software (FOSS). You may have come across the term before, but what does it mean? Well, the “free” bit is fairly straightforward - free software is software that you don’t have to pay for.</p>

<p>But what about the “Open Source” part? Well, Open Source software means that the code that makes up the software has been published online, and is available for anyone to review and even to adapt and change for their own purposes.</p>

<h1 id="how-noble-whats-the-catch">How noble… what’s the catch?</h1>

<p>You’re right to be skeptical in these trying times. We all know there is no such thing as a free lunch. Why would people go to the effort of making entire applications, and then just give them away?</p>

<p>There are actually a number of reasons. One possibility, is that people are using it to showcase their talents, with the view to generating interest in other things they want to sell. Perhaps offering a <a href="https://chromewebstore.google.com/detail/nownextlater-extension/hmeicodhjdadobfkagbmjgkpgfmdnmhj?hl=en">completely free Chrome extension</a>, that links back to the portfolio website they use to generate business.</p>

<p>Others make money not from the software itself, which they give away freely, but from selling service packages to help you install and manage the product.</p>

<p>Still others just want to solve a personal issue that’s been bugging them. Perhaps they need a way to put a customisable blog online. Having solved the problem, they put the code online and soon others are contributing, adding their own ideas. Before you know it, there’s a whole community around the software, and it’s the <a href="https://wordpress.org/">most popular free CMS</a> platform on the planet.</p>

<p>Finally, there is a subset of FOSS that is perhaps much more recognisable to the capitalist world. Companies - yes companies - like Oracle or the <strong><a href="https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/">Mozilla Foundation</a></strong> create lots of software in the way a “normal” software company does, but they are funded by grants or other charitable activities. The software they give away is as professional, secure, and feature rich as anything else, but they do not operate for a profit.</p>

<p>Regardless of the origins of your FOSS, there are some things to consider. We’ll come back to those at the end, but for now let’s explore what your FOSS options are. This is by no means an extensive list - something like that would be nearly impossible to collate. Instead, this is a list of the tools I think are the best fit for small organisations with limited budget and IT capacity. They straddle the line between functionality, ease of use, and (obviously) price. If you’re looking to dip your toes in the waters of FOSS, then this list might just help you out.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can also get your FOSS fix by heading to the <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/resource-centre/">Resource Centre</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="lets-get-our-foss-on">Let’s get our FOSS on…</h1>

<figure>

<figure>
  <img src="https://willrc.co.uk/content/images/libreoffice-1024x205.png" alt="" class="post-image " style="" />
  <figcaption class="post-image-caption"></figcaption>
</figure>

<figcaption>

Screenshots of the LibreOffice suite - Writer, Calc, and Impress. Taken from the [LibreOffice website](https://www.libreoffice.org/discover/libreoffice/).

</figcaption>

</figure>

<h2 id="want-to-ditch-microsoft-office-try-libreoffice">Want to ditch Microsoft Office? Try LibreOffice.</h2>

<p>Perhaps the first question on your mind if you’re thinking about switching software is “how will I type my documents?”. Well, ask any nerd IT professional, and their first answer is likely to be <a href="https://www.libreoffice.org/"><strong>LibreOffice</strong></a>. A veritable crown-jewel in the FOSS pantheon.</p>

<p>I say “crown-jewel”… Look, I’ll say it right off the bat. For those used to the hyper polished look of Microsoft or Apple products, you might not think this the prettiest software on the list. Don’t let that fool you though, what it lacks in sleekness, it makes up for in functionality. And, you know, being completely free. You’ll get more or less everything you’ll need from an Office suite - with Writer, Calc, and Impress ready to take the reins from Word, Excel, and PowerPoint respectively.</p>

<p>Will this give you everything that Microsoft Word will? Unfortunately not. One of the major benefits of the Microsoft 365 architecture is the ability to near-seamlessly document share and collaborate. Whether that’s through SharePoint, via Teams, or even directly sharing a document and having a colleague work with you in real time. These things are not available to LibreOffice users.</p>

<p>It is also worth noting that, while LibreOffice can open and read, for example, Word documents, sometimes the formatting is specific to the Microsoft-owned .docx file type, and so you may experience some weird text placements moving from one software to another.</p>

<p>But, if those things aren’t deal breakers for you, then you can pick yourself up an established, supported, and robust Office Suite for the princely sum of £0. And hey, if it works for city councils ranging from <a href="https://joinup.ec.europa.eu/collection/open-source-observatory-osor/news/limerick-city-council-increas">Limerick</a> to <a href="https://itsfoss.com/barcelona-open-source/">Barcelona</a>, then it’s probably worth some thought?</p>

<figure>

<figure>
  <img src="https://willrc.co.uk/content/images/image-1024x566.jpg" alt="" class="post-image " style="" />
  <figcaption class="post-image-caption"></figcaption>
</figure>

<figcaption>

GIMP - the GNU Image Manipulation Programme. Image taken from the [GIMP](https://www.gimp.org/) website.

</figcaption>

</figure>

<h2 id="editing-images-check-out-gimp">Editing images? Check out GIMP.</h2>

<p>The GNU Image Manipulation Programme is a… well it’s a programme that allows you to manipulate images… Whether you want to touch up some holiday photos, or create your own artwork from scratch, GIMP might well be the only tool you need.</p>

<p>As a Photoshop replacement, it gets you most of the way there. What you can’t do out of the box, you might be able to find in the form of extensions, or in presets that other users have uploaded.</p>

<p>GNU, incidentally, is a collection of free software that can come together as a whole Operating System, or be used as parts within other Operating Systems. It stands for “GNU is not Unix”, for nerd reasons.</p>

<figure>

<figure>
  <img src="https://willrc.co.uk/content/images/shotcut-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="post-image " style="" />
  <figcaption class="post-image-caption"></figcaption>
</figure>

<figcaption>

Screenshot of Shotcut, taken from the [Shotcut](https://www.shotcut.org/) website.

</figcaption>

</figure>

<h2 id="need-to-edit-video-content-use-shotcut">Need to edit video content? Use Shotcut</h2>

<p>You can’t search for “free video editor” without coming across Blender, one of the darlings of the FOSS ecosystem. A fully fledged graphics tool that can do everything from edit your videos to create and render 3D animation. It’s a fantastic product, but comes with a huge learning curve.</p>

<p>Less well known, but my personal go-to, is <a href="https://www.shotcut.org/"><strong>Shotcut</strong></a>. If all you need is a tool to edit some videos - perhaps for creating online content - I highly recommend checking this out. It’s simple to use, but comes with some powerful features. It’s my go to software for editing HowTo videos before I send them to clients, including things like adding preset title cards, captions, and all the usual transitions (who doesn’t love a good star-wipe?).</p>

<p><strong>Bonus video related software:</strong> If you want to capture video - maybe record your screen for a tutorial video, or stream your gaming session for your Twitch followers, then have a look at <a href="https://obsproject.com/"><strong>OBS</strong></a>.</p>

<figure>

<figure>
  <img src="https://willrc.co.uk/content/images/image-1-1024x863.jpg" alt="" class="post-image " style="" />
  <figcaption class="post-image-caption"></figcaption>
</figure>

<figcaption>

Firefox, taken from the [Firefox](https://www.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/new/) website.

</figcaption>

</figure>

<h2 id="in-need-of-a-foss-web-browser-i-use-firefox">In need of a FOSS web browser? I use Firefox</h2>

<p>Statistically speaking, you’re reading this from a Chrome browser. For a long while now, Chrome has ruled the roost in the “things I access the internet with”. Recently though, I made the switch from Chrome to <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/new/"><strong>Firefox</strong></a>. Why? Well I actually wrote a whole blog post about it. But in typical fashion, that whole post can probably be summed up in two bullet points:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Chrome was taking up a lot of resources, noticeably slowing down my laptop</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I wanted to move away from Google and put my support into something Free and Open Source</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Firefox is where I landed. Philosophically, I like what the Mozilla Foundation are doing, and - as importantly - Firefox is a great browser. If you’ve been on Chrome for any length of time, you’ll likely have a number of extensions that you don’t want to lose. The good news is that a lot of the better-known extensions exist on both browsers. You can also import all your history and bookmarks over as well, should you feel the need.</p>

<p><strong>Bonus Mozilla tip:</strong> If you’re in the market for an email client (maybe new Outlook is causing you grief) you should check out <strong><a href="https://www.thunderbird.net/en-US/">Thunderbird</a></strong>, also from Mozilla. There are some caveats if you still have a Microsoft 365 email, but if you’re on Google or another client, then it’s a very good option.</p>

<h1 id="some-other-things-to-consider">Some other things to consider</h1>

<p>When you get a Microsoft 365 environment, or you setup a Google Workspace for your company, it’s not just the access to applications you’re getting. For most of those, there are FOSS alternatives.</p>

<p>But you’re also getting things like cloud storage, some form of cyber protection, and, if you’re in charge of multiple users, the ability to centrally manage your infrastructure. On top of all that, you’re also getting access to email, alternatives for which we haven’t covered here (watch this space).</p>

<p>If none of those things are super important to you - maybe you’re a one-person setup, or a very small team that doesn’t need a central file share - then some of these options will genuinely give you everything you need.</p>

<p>Equally, if you are a larger organisation - perhaps a school or research institution - you can get some SLA (Service Level Agreements) on tools like LibreOffice. You still don’t pay anything for the software, but you pay for support and service management. For many, this is a good middle ground.</p>

<p>But jumping wholesale into the FOSS ecosystem isn’t for everybody - and that’s ok! The great news is that it’s not an all-or-nothing option. Just because you need to stick with Microsoft for your email and office suite, doesn’t mean you can’t check out Shortcut for your video editing, or GIMP for your images.</p>

<p>Free and Open Source Software is built on the philosophy that good quality software should be accessible to everyone. If that’s something you think you can get on board with, then why not explore some of those options today?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thinking about replacing some of your paid-for apps with FOSS alternatives? Book a <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/contact/">free 20 minute chat</a> with me to talk through any questions!</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="guides" /><category term="foss" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Intro - what is FOSS? Free and Open Source Software (FOSS). You may have come across the term before, but what does it mean? Well, the “free” bit is fairly straightforward - free software is software that you don’t have to pay for. But what about the “Open Source” part? Well, Open Source software means that the code that makes up the software has been published online, and is available for anyone to review and even to adapt and change for their own purposes. How noble… what’s the catch? You’re right to be skeptical in these trying times. We all know there is no such thing as a free lunch. Why would people go to the effort of making entire applications, and then just give them away? There are actually a number of reasons. One possibility, is that people are using it to showcase their talents, with the view to generating interest in other things they want to sell. Perhaps offering a completely free Chrome extension, that links back to the portfolio website they use to generate business. Others make money not from the software itself, which they give away freely, but from selling service packages to help you install and manage the product. Still others just want to solve a personal issue that’s been bugging them. Perhaps they need a way to put a customisable blog online. Having solved the problem, they put the code online and soon others are contributing, adding their own ideas. Before you know it, there’s a whole community around the software, and it’s the most popular free CMS platform on the planet. Finally, there is a subset of FOSS that is perhaps much more recognisable to the capitalist world. Companies - yes companies - like Oracle or the Mozilla Foundation create lots of software in the way a “normal” software company does, but they are funded by grants or other charitable activities. The software they give away is as professional, secure, and feature rich as anything else, but they do not operate for a profit. Regardless of the origins of your FOSS, there are some things to consider. We’ll come back to those at the end, but for now let’s explore what your FOSS options are. This is by no means an extensive list - something like that would be nearly impossible to collate. Instead, this is a list of the tools I think are the best fit for small organisations with limited budget and IT capacity. They straddle the line between functionality, ease of use, and (obviously) price. If you’re looking to dip your toes in the waters of FOSS, then this list might just help you out. You can also get your FOSS fix by heading to the Resource Centre. Let’s get our FOSS on… Screenshots of the LibreOffice suite - Writer, Calc, and Impress. Taken from the [LibreOffice website](https://www.libreoffice.org/discover/libreoffice/). Want to ditch Microsoft Office? Try LibreOffice. Perhaps the first question on your mind if you’re thinking about switching software is “how will I type my documents?”. Well, ask any nerd IT professional, and their first answer is likely to be LibreOffice. A veritable crown-jewel in the FOSS pantheon. I say “crown-jewel”… Look, I’ll say it right off the bat. For those used to the hyper polished look of Microsoft or Apple products, you might not think this the prettiest software on the list. Don’t let that fool you though, what it lacks in sleekness, it makes up for in functionality. And, you know, being completely free. You’ll get more or less everything you’ll need from an Office suite - with Writer, Calc, and Impress ready to take the reins from Word, Excel, and PowerPoint respectively. Will this give you everything that Microsoft Word will? Unfortunately not. One of the major benefits of the Microsoft 365 architecture is the ability to near-seamlessly document share and collaborate. Whether that’s through SharePoint, via Teams, or even directly sharing a document and having a colleague work with you in real time. These things are not available to LibreOffice users. It is also worth noting that, while LibreOffice can open and read, for example, Word documents, sometimes the formatting is specific to the Microsoft-owned .docx file type, and so you may experience some weird text placements moving from one software to another. But, if those things aren’t deal breakers for you, then you can pick yourself up an established, supported, and robust Office Suite for the princely sum of £0. And hey, if it works for city councils ranging from Limerick to Barcelona, then it’s probably worth some thought? GIMP - the GNU Image Manipulation Programme. Image taken from the [GIMP](https://www.gimp.org/) website. Editing images? Check out GIMP. The GNU Image Manipulation Programme is a… well it’s a programme that allows you to manipulate images… Whether you want to touch up some holiday photos, or create your own artwork from scratch, GIMP might well be the only tool you need. As a Photoshop replacement, it gets you most of the way there. What you can’t do out of the box, you might be able to find in the form of extensions, or in presets that other users have uploaded. GNU, incidentally, is a collection of free software that can come together as a whole Operating System, or be used as parts within other Operating Systems. It stands for “GNU is not Unix”, for nerd reasons. Screenshot of Shotcut, taken from the [Shotcut](https://www.shotcut.org/) website. Need to edit video content? Use Shotcut You can’t search for “free video editor” without coming across Blender, one of the darlings of the FOSS ecosystem. A fully fledged graphics tool that can do everything from edit your videos to create and render 3D animation. It’s a fantastic product, but comes with a huge learning curve. Less well known, but my personal go-to, is Shotcut. If all you need is a tool to edit some videos - perhaps for creating online content - I highly recommend checking this out. It’s simple to use, but comes with some powerful features. It’s my go to software for editing HowTo videos before I send them to clients, including things like adding preset title cards, captions, and all the usual transitions (who doesn’t love a good star-wipe?). Bonus video related software: If you want to capture video - maybe record your screen for a tutorial video, or stream your gaming session for your Twitch followers, then have a look at OBS. Firefox, taken from the [Firefox](https://www.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/new/) website. In need of a FOSS web browser? I use Firefox Statistically speaking, you’re reading this from a Chrome browser. For a long while now, Chrome has ruled the roost in the “things I access the internet with”. Recently though, I made the switch from Chrome to Firefox. Why? Well I actually wrote a whole blog post about it. But in typical fashion, that whole post can probably be summed up in two bullet points: Chrome was taking up a lot of resources, noticeably slowing down my laptop I wanted to move away from Google and put my support into something Free and Open Source Firefox is where I landed. Philosophically, I like what the Mozilla Foundation are doing, and - as importantly - Firefox is a great browser. If you’ve been on Chrome for any length of time, you’ll likely have a number of extensions that you don’t want to lose. The good news is that a lot of the better-known extensions exist on both browsers. You can also import all your history and bookmarks over as well, should you feel the need. Bonus Mozilla tip: If you’re in the market for an email client (maybe new Outlook is causing you grief) you should check out Thunderbird, also from Mozilla. There are some caveats if you still have a Microsoft 365 email, but if you’re on Google or another client, then it’s a very good option. Some other things to consider When you get a Microsoft 365 environment, or you setup a Google Workspace for your company, it’s not just the access to applications you’re getting. For most of those, there are FOSS alternatives. But you’re also getting things like cloud storage, some form of cyber protection, and, if you’re in charge of multiple users, the ability to centrally manage your infrastructure. On top of all that, you’re also getting access to email, alternatives for which we haven’t covered here (watch this space). If none of those things are super important to you - maybe you’re a one-person setup, or a very small team that doesn’t need a central file share - then some of these options will genuinely give you everything you need. Equally, if you are a larger organisation - perhaps a school or research institution - you can get some SLA (Service Level Agreements) on tools like LibreOffice. You still don’t pay anything for the software, but you pay for support and service management. For many, this is a good middle ground. But jumping wholesale into the FOSS ecosystem isn’t for everybody - and that’s ok! The great news is that it’s not an all-or-nothing option. Just because you need to stick with Microsoft for your email and office suite, doesn’t mean you can’t check out Shortcut for your video editing, or GIMP for your images. Free and Open Source Software is built on the philosophy that good quality software should be accessible to everyone. If that’s something you think you can get on board with, then why not explore some of those options today? Thinking about replacing some of your paid-for apps with FOSS alternatives? Book a free 20 minute chat with me to talk through any questions!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/foss-genai.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/foss-genai.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">ChatGPT vs Copilot</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/chatgpt-vs-copilot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ChatGPT vs Copilot" /><published>2024-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/chatgpt-vs-copilot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/chatgpt-vs-copilot/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been using both ChatGPT4 and Microsoft Copilot for a couple of months. Weirdly, I couldn’t find a <a href="https://tech.co/news/chatgpt-vs-microsoft-copilot">single post</a> by <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/microsoft-copilot-pro-vs-openais-chatgpt-plus-which-is-worth-your-20-a-month/">anyone</a> who had <a href="https://www.uctoday.com/unified-communications/chatgpt-vs-microsoft-copilot-the-major-differences/">reviewed their experiences</a> of it. So, I thought I’d throw in my two cents.</p>

<figure>

![Google Trends graph showing interest in the search term "Copilot vs ChatGPT" over the last 12 months. Graph shows a sharp increase in interest in the last 3 months.](images/copilot-chatgpt-google-trends-1024x402.png)

<figcaption>

Google Trends graph showing interest in the search term "Copilot vs ChatGPT" over the last 12 months.

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p>My main takeaway is that, as with a lot of technology, “which tool is better?” depends entirely on what you’re using it for. If you want the spoiler alert right up top, I end up deciding that, if you aren’t already embedded in Microsoft 365, for the average person ChatGPT will likely be the better call. There are quite a few caveats though, so do read on.</p>

<p><strong>For clarity’s sake, throughout I’m talking about OpenAI’s <a href="https://openai.com/chatgpt">ChatGPT-4</a>, and Microsoft’s <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/enterprise/copilot-for-microsoft-365">Copilot for Microsoft 365</a>.</strong></p>

<p>As well as some general observations about the benefits, I talk through two real-world tasks that I’ve done in the last month, to give a sense of where you might see the platforms limitations.</p>

<p>Let’s dive in!</p>

<h2 id="test-1-working-with-excel-data">Test 1: Working with Excel data</h2>

<p>Over at <a href="https://esmeefairbairn.org.uk/">Esmée Fairbairn Foundation</a>, we’re in the process of running a Youth Led Creativity Fund, and part of my work for that is to design and build the infrastructure behind it. Last week, this included allocating the 10 judges from our Involving Young People Collective to the 350-something applications we received for the fund.</p>

<p>There are lots of ways one might choose to tackle this challenge. As the Technology Lead at the Foundation though, I’ve paid for a Copilot license to test out exactly what this can do. So I figured why do any real work myself?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s a myth that getting AI means you don’t have to do any work.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are some stipulations to the allocations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Each application must be judged by two judges.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>We do not want to repeat judging pairs too often.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>And, as the final stipulation that you don’t have to tacitly acknowledge to humans, but you do to computers, a judge cannot assess the same application twice.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I had all the applications in a spreadsheet, so Copilot seemed like the obvious play here. One of the major selling points of Copilot is that it sits right in your Microsoft 365 apps.</p>

<h3 id="so-how-did-microsofts-copilot-do">So how did Microsoft’s Copilot do?</h3>

<p>So, here’s the prompt I ran for Copilot for Excel:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In Table 1 there are 350 applications, each of which needs to be assessed by two judges. The names of the judges are in Table 2. Can you assign two judges to each application - using columns C and D - making sure that no judging pair is used more frequently than others, and that no judge assesses the same application twice?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And so Copilot got to thinking. And then it did a bit more thinking. And then, for good measure, it thought some more. Finally, Copilot spits out an answer. Great!</p>

<p>It can’t make any edits to the spreadsheet itself. Less great. But it will tell me what I need to do. That’s fine - giving me a formula is still taking some of the grunt work off me, so I’ll take it. What follows is a long answer about needed to create random numbers for each judge, and then using those numbers it can assign judges to each application. I don’t fully understand this, but that’s what I’m paying the AI for, so I do what it asks. The instructions themselves are relatively clear, though it’s still annoying that it can’t do any of this itself.</p>

<p>I follow the instructions for both columns, and viola! It does it perfectly! For the first 10 applications. Then the spreadsheet throws up the dreaded <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#REF!</code> error for each of the following 340-something. Not ideal.</p>

<p>So, I plug my own brain back in and realise that it has assigned the 10 judges to the first 10 applications, but that the formula doesn’t account for the fact that the judges need to have more than 2 applications each.</p>

<p>So, I go back to Copilot to explain the little misunderstanding. It offers some sincere apologies and then reworks the formula for me. Back and forth this goes for a little while, with none of the options working.</p>

<p>I’m wasn’t getting anywhere, so eventually I simplified the problem. I didn’t need AI to assign <em>both</em> judges. Because each judge is assessing roughly the same number of applications, I can just use the old drag cell method to assign judges in repeating order for the first column. Once I’ve done that, I just need Copilot to assign the second judge. Surely that’s easier?</p>

<p>Reader, it was not.</p>

<p>Even after a few more exchanges, it kept giving me broken formulas. I don’t mean that the formulas gave me the wrong information. I mean that the syntax of the formula was incorrect. I know enough about Excel to work out where the formula didn’t work, so after a little manual effort I fixed it myself and ran it. But even when the formula gave an output, it was repeating judging pairs with almost perfect consistency.</p>

<p>I went back to Copilot, gave it the fixed formula, and reminded it that I needed to mix up the judging pairs as much as possible. At that point, Copilot basically gave up, and offered me the start of a VBA script that might get me some of the way there.</p>

<p>I’d spent nearly half an hour trying to get this to work, and it was rapidly becoming apparent that either I’m not good at prompt engineering, or Copilot just fundamentally wasn’t capable of providing what I needed. Now, clearly, I’m a fantastic prompt engineer, as those of you who have read my <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/articles/ai-as-a-creative-tool/">AI-generated Billy Joel homage</a> will know.</p>

<p>So I gave up on Copilot, and decided to see what ChatGPT could do…</p>

<h3 id="using-openais-chatgpt">Using OpenAI’s ChatGPT</h3>

<p>Before I get into my experience with ChatGPT, there’s a very important point I need to make. While using Copilot, all of the data I was working with remained within my organisation’s infrastructure. Our Privacy Policy doesn’t yet mention anything about ChatGPT, so I didn’t have consent from either the applicants or the judges to upload their data to that third party. So, before I did anything, I needed to anonymise the data. This wasn’t difficult or particularly time-consuming, but I mention it for two reasons. One, it was another step I had to take, and that speaks to my point about AI not always being the quick and easy silver bullet. Two, it’s a very important step that a lot of organisations or individuals might not think to take.</p>

<p>Anyway, with a new spreadsheet of anonymous information, I hit up ChatGPT with the following prompt.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I have a spreadsheet of applications that I need to allocate judges to. I’ve already allocated the first judge, but I need to allocate a second one. Each application cannot be judged by the same person twice, and I want to minimise the number of times a judging pair is repeated. The spreadsheet has the allocations on a sheet called “Allocations”, and the Judge names on a sheet called “Judges”. Please can you fill out the “Judge 2” column on the allocations sheet with allocations.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Again, at the risk of labouring the point, what I’d actually given it was a list of unique IDs pulled from our organisation’s CRM instead of the names of the applications, and a list of “Judge A, Judge B, Judge C….” instead of the names of the judges. This doesn’t matter to the AI - it’s just sorting data. But it gets me what I want (minus a little script work at the other end) without having to give the names of either organisations or people to a third party application.</p>

<p>As you can see, I’d jumped straight into “easy mode”, giving ChatGPT the spreadsheet with Judge 1 already allocated. It made my life easier because a) I already had the sheet there, and b) it meant I had to think less hard about the prompt I was giving.</p>

<p>ChatGPT responded immediately, saying:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Certainly, I can help with that. Please upload the spreadsheet you mentioned. Once I have the file, I can analyze the existing allocations and propose a second judge for each application, ensuring that no application is judged by the same person twice and that judge pairs are not often repeated.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What I liked about this response was that it was explaining back to me what it was going to do in very clear terms. It had understood what I needed.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>ChatGPT confirms what you’re asking of it, and then lets you know how it’s going to do it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So I uploaded my anonymised spreadsheet and let ChatGPT do its thing. It spent a lot of time analysing. To be fair to Copilot, ChatGPT took as long, if not slightly longer, to come back to me. I thought about giving a point to Microsoft for that but then remembered that the whole reason I was using ChatGPT was because Microsoft couldn’t do what I’d asked. I kept the point.</p>

<p>Slightly less than an eon later (not quite 5 minutes), I got the following response:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I have allocated a second judge to each application, ensuring that no judge is assigned to the same application twice and minimizing repeat judge pairings. You can download the updated spreadsheet using the link below:</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yes, that’s right, not only had it done the calculations for me, but it had put it all into a nice new spreadsheet for me to download and use.</p>

<p>Of course, I needed to go back in and un-anonymise the data again. But compared to manually allocating 10 judges to 350 applications, this seemed like a huge win. All told, including the time it took me to anonymise the table, write the prompt, wait for ChatGPT to do the work, un-anonymising the output, and lastly do some spot checks to make sure it had given me what I needed, no more than 15 minutes went by.</p>

<h3 id="the-winner-chatgpt-by-a-lot">The winner: ChatGPT (by a lot)</h3>

<p>I don’t know how long it would take me to have done this manually. I don’t mean manually-manually - adding 10 judges to 350 applications, making sure as few repeated pairs as possible would have taken me all day. What I mean is that I don’t know how I would have gone about that from a formula perspective. Before turning to AI, I had tried with PivotTables, but I didn’t get very far. I could have Googled it, I’m sure, or brought in one of my data colleagues. But Googling would have eaten into my day, with no immediate promise of success. And bringing in a colleague means taking up their time and capacity. The point of AI is to free up capacity in exactly this kind of way.</p>

<p>And if that is the metric, then it’s clear that ChatGPT is the winner. Even if Copilot had given me the right formula, without too much fuss, it was still a comparatively manual process. As it was, I had to really work to get any output at all. With ChatGPT, I told it what I wanted, I gave it the data, and then I didn’t even have time to make myself a cup of tea before it had done the work for me.</p>

<p>But this was a specific scenario that isn’t going to be something everyone does day-to-day. What about all the other stuff your average office worker might do?</p>

<h2 id="copilot-is-built-into-your-microsoft-environment">Copilot is built into your Microsoft environment</h2>

<p>Maybe my first use case was a little taxing for something that is still technically in preview. But one of the big selling points is that Copilot sits across your whole Microsoft organisation. There’s even a dedicated Copilot chat pinned to the top of your Teams application.</p>

<p>Microsoft has been gearing up for this kind of integration for years. In fact, “AI” products have been part of the Office 365 platform for a while now. If you’ve ever used the PowerPoint designer tool, that is by a broad definition Generative AI. Even before Office 365, anyone who used Word in the late 90s and kept having to tell Clippy “No, I’m not writing a letter, get lost!” will know that we’ve had the power to do low-level AI-based generation for decades.</p>

<figure>

![Clippy, the late-90s "intelligent user interface" for Microsoft Word, asking whether the user needs help writing a letter.](images/Clippy-Letter.png)

<figcaption>

Clippy, who walked so Copilot could walk slightly faster.

</figcaption>

</figure>

<p>If I ignore my little issue with Excel - which again, to be fair, Microsoft does say is in Preview - there are dozens of other use cases where Copilot could make my life easier. With this in mind, I dove into the Teams chat function.</p>

<p>I’d been having some back and forth with a colleague from finance about an upcoming audit. There was a particular document I wanted to get hold of, and I knew he’d emailed it to me a couple of weeks ago. I could have just searched Outlook, but everybody knows that’s a good way to lose 2 hours to fruitlessly rewording your search terms. I know it’s terrible practice to use Outlook as a repository for files. I know that as soon as I get an attachment that I know will be useful, I should load it up into SharePoint. I know that. You know that. But come on, who actually does that? Really? And besides, why can’t Microsoft just give us an email client that has good search functionality?</p>

<p>Well, with Copilot, we don’t need one! I can ask it for something, and it will search the whole of my infrastructure to give me contextually useful information. Except, it can’t… When I asked Copilot in Teams to fetch me an email I knew that our auditors had sent us, it spent nearly 2 full minutes searching before it told me that it couldn’t find anything. I hopped over to Outlook and found the email in less than 30 seconds.</p>

<p>Ok, so that’s not a win either. Maybe let’s give it a different type of task…</p>

<h2 id="test-2-planning-my-day">Test 2: Planning my day</h2>

<p>Unlike the Excel problem, which I genuinely needed to get done and therefore have only really thought of as a head-to-head test retrospectively, for this I wanted to be a little more rigorous. We’ll see how that went…</p>

<p>I gave both tools the same prompt: “Act as my personal assistant and help me plan my day. Here are the things I need to get done…” followed by a list of about 10 things, each with a rough amount of time for how long I thought it might take (“look into Microsoft Planner as an alternative to Jira - 40mins”, for example).</p>

<p>Copilot has access to my calendar, whereas ChatGPT does not. Clearly, the advantage here, from a real-world use case scenario, should go to Microsoft. For Copilot, I added the line “The things already in my calendar are immovable”. For ChatGPT, I added “I also have the following meetings in my calendar:…”</p>

<p>The results for both were… mixed…</p>

<h3 id="copilot">Copilot</h3>

<p>Copilot identified the commitments already in my calendar and worked around them. In the order that I’d given the tasks, it printed out a schedule that filled in the gaps around my meetings. When it got to 6pm, it told me that I could “…also use the time after 6 PM to complete the remaining tasks on [my] to-do list”. This, to me, seemed like a good result. I hadn’t specified any priorities, so it makes sense that it ran the schedule in the order I gave the tasks.</p>

<p>Except… it didn’t put them into my calendar. When I followed up and explicitly asked it to do so, it told me that it was unable, and gave me instructions for how to do it myself. There seems to be a real hit-and-miss set of rules that dictate which parts of your environment Copilot can interact with directly. I understand it not being able to delete events, for example. What if it mistakenly deletes something important? But adding them surely can’t be a world-ending situation, can it Microsoft?</p>

<p>I think this one irked me more because what is the point of a digital assistant if I still have to do most of the legwork? I use time-blocking quite a lot to manage my day. So by the time I’ve explained all of the tasks I have to Copilot, if it then needs me to put them in the Calendar myself the whole process is pointless.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>An AI assistant is only so useful, if you still have to do most of the legwork.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To be honest, it annoyed me so much that I didn’t even bother trying to make changes to the prompt. I moved straight onto ChatGPT. So much for a rigorous head-to-head.</p>

<h3 id="chatgpt">ChatGPT</h3>

<p>Much like Copilot, ChatGPT gave me a breakdown of my day with tasks in the order I had given them. Unlike Copilot, it had formatted it nicely into morning, afternoon, and evening sections. ChatGPT had even put in a half-hour lunch break at midday, and 30 minutes at the end of the day to “Wrap up and review tasks for the day”. How nice of it. I suppose this was its way of directly responding to the “Act as my personal assistant” part of the prompt.</p>

<p>And then things got weird. I followed up with the prompt “I also need to walk the dog for half an hour at some point this afternoon, can you fit that in?”. It had already put some of my meetings into the evening, lacking an apparent sense of work/life balance (adding lunch aside), I assumed it would just shove in “3.30-4pm: Dog walking” and move everything else back 30 mins. It’s what I would have done.</p>

<p>It did not do that. In fact, in the Evening section, it provided me with the following:</p>

<p><strong>Morning:</strong><br />
<strong>10:30 - 11:00:</strong> All-hands meeting<br />
<strong>11:00 - 12:00:</strong> Sort out email templates…<br />
<strong>12:00 - 12:30:</strong> Lunch break</p>

<p><strong>Afternoon:</strong><br />
<strong>12:30 - 13:30:</strong> Call with…<br />
<strong>13:30 - 14:00:</strong> Sort out…<br />
<strong>14:00 - 14:15:</strong> Change address with…<br />
<strong>14:15 - 14:45:</strong> Look into MS Planner as an alternative to Jira<br />
<strong>14:45 - 15:25:</strong> Look at credits for Azure storage<br />
<strong>15:25 - 15:35:</strong> Pay outstanding…<br />
<strong>15:35 - 15:50:</strong> Check in with…<br />
<strong>15:50 - 16:05:</strong> Pay…<br />
<strong>16:05 - 16:20:</strong> Follow up on…<br />
<strong>16:20 - 16:30:</strong> Wrap up and review tasks for the day</p>

<p><strong>Evening:</strong><br />
<strong>14:30 - 15:00:</strong> Walk the dog</p>

<p><em>The formatting has been amended slightly, and some entries have been redacted.</em></p>

<p>It had left the afternoon section untouched, leaving in the previous schedule across the 2.30pm-3pm slot. ChatGPT obviously understood that I needed 30 mins to walk the dog, and that it needed to be in the afternoon, as it assigned the 2.30-3pm time to it. But it then just tacked it onto the end of the day, rather than amend what else was going on.</p>

<p>At first, I thought maybe ChatGPT had some kind of moral aversion to me running a personal errand in the middle of the afternoon. So I switched it. I gave it the follow-up prompt: “I’ve got a dog-walker now, so I don’t need to walk the dog. However, I now have a conference call that runs from 2.30pm to 3pm. Can you adjust my schedule?”. “Of course!” The answer immediately came back, before it gave me the same output but replacing “Walk the dog” with “Conference call” in the evening slot.</p>

<p>I tried several different prompts, each as unsuccessful as the last. Eventually, I shut down that chat window and opened up a fresh one, giving it roughly the same initial prompt, but putting the conference call in from the start. It handled that mostly correctly, though it put the call in at the end of the day despite my telling it that it was fixed for 2.30pm. Once I clarified that though, it sent me back an amended schedule with no errors - though interestingly it no longer split it into Morning, Afternoon, and Evening segments. I even asked it to rearrange the tasks so that the Azure credits task was earlier in the day, and it amended the schedule fine. Just for giggles, I threw the dog walking question back in (“I forgot that I need to walk my dog for 30 mins this afternoon. Can you schedule that in?”), and it put that in for 3.30pm and arranged everything else around it. As a final test, I asked it to put it just after lunch instead. It put it in for the morning, but when I asked it to correct itself, it did.</p>

<h3 id="the-winner-no-one">The winner: …no one?</h3>

<p>I liked that ChatGPT added in little things like a lunch break and time to wrap up at the end of the day. Most of the time, it looks like it can handle the task pretty well. However, from the looks of it if ChatGPT trips itself up it can be hard to put it back on track.</p>

<p>As for Copilot… I struggled with this. I’ll come onto this more in a second, but from a financial point of view it is a larger commitment (you have to buy a one-year license). On top of that one of the major selling points is that it sits within your Microsoft infrastructure. But if it can’t add things to my calendar for me, what is the point? ChatGPT can’t do this either, but it doesn’t claim to be integrated.</p>

<p>To be fair, this is perhaps a slightly contrived test scenario. So I thought a little more about how I would actually use a service like this. I opened up a new Copilot chat and gave it the prompt “Someone’s asked for a call at 3pm. Do I have time, and if so can you put a hold in my calendar.” 45 seconds later (yes, I timed it) it came back to tell me that I already had a call at 2pm that looked like it would run until 3.30, and therefore I would be unlikely to make the 3pm call. It also confirmed that, even if I had the time, it couldn’t put the hold in for me, as it was unable to add things to my calendar. I reset my stopwatch and then timed how long it took me to open up my Calendar, look at the 3pm slot, and then add a hold into that time anyway. 12 seconds. I also saw that in that time slot I had a conflicting meeting at 3pm anyway, which Copilot didn’t tell me about.</p>

<figure>

![Screenshot of Copilot response to the question "Do I have time for a call at 3pm, and can you put it in my calendar?" The response was that I have a call already, and that Copilot cannot add events into my calendar.](images/copilot-call-at-3pm.png)

<figcaption>

Screenshot of Copilot's response to a query about my availability for a call.

</figcaption>

</figure>

<h2 id="so-what-is-copilot-good-for">So what is Copilot good for?</h2>

<p>I think, to be honest, the majority of the use I’ve got from Copilot is in summarising things. I get brought into long email threads relatively often, and instead of having to read through 30 emails to get a sense of what’s going on, a click of the Copilot button in Outlook gives me a decent summary to get started.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Copilot really shines in Teams meetings.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Similarly, one of the absolute best uses I’ve had for Copilot has been as an assistant in Teams meetings. If you record calls and enable transcripts, Copilot can offer real-time summaries of what’s being said, alongside citations and direct quotes. Once the meeting has ended, you can review summaries and action points, even splitting it out by person. If you were in an entirely Teams-based meeting - by which I mean everyone on the call has signed in, rather than a Hybrid situation where some of your team are together in a room and others are dialing in - you can see breakdowns of how much each person spoke, and click through visual representations of what was said when so you can see the recording for yourself.</p>

<p>Of course, there are caveats to all of this. The first, and most obvious, is that you need to be having a Teams call for this to work. If your organisation isn’t already on Microsoft, this is going to be a big investment. Even if you have Microsoft 365, but tend to use Zoom, or Slack, to run your meetings, paying for Copilot might not be the smartest move. Incidentally, <a href="https://www.zoom.com/en/ai-assistant/">Zoom does have an equivalent</a> AI meeting assistant, which gets very good reviews. It also comes included with every paid plan, compared to Copilot’s add-on fee.</p>

<p>The second major caveat is that the call needs to be recorded, which means you’ll need permission from everyone on the call for that to be the case. This might well be fine for internal calls, but if you want to use Copilot to help you take notes on calls with clients, you’ll need to adjust your Privacy Policies.</p>

<p>For someone in my position though, at an organisation that predominantly works with Microsoft products, Copilot for Teams is a game changer. I absolutely love it. For me, the summaries of the meetings alone are worth it, meaning you can pay less attention to note taking and be more present in the call. You can also query the notes after the fact, directly from the Teams app (“The meeting I had last Thursday about Data Privacy - what was Barry’s point about the cost-benefit of external providers?”).</p>

<h2 id="so-which-should-i-get">So which should I get?</h2>

<p>I so badly want to recommend Copilot. But while get a huge amount of value from Copilot for Teams, with regards to the rest of the platform…</p>

<p>I don’t get the value of it as an AI chat assistant or as an omni-search for my organisation. I, personally, get zero value from it for PowerPoint and Excel (in fact it actively angers me for Excel). Word is a bit of a middle ground. I don’t get a lot of use from it, but I think that is in large part because that is where ChatGPT and Copilot overlap so obviously. As someone lucky enough to have subscriptions to both, I tend to default to ChatGPT. If I didn’t also have ChatGPT, I might get more out of Copilot for Word.</p>

<p>Beyond that though, if I were offering a recommendation to a small/medium sized organisation, I think my overriding consideration is that you can only buy Copilot as a yearly license. Yes, the two platforms cost roughly the same when you consider them over a year, but you have to buy the full year with Copilot. At a cost of £300 per user, this might not be the right call for an organisation looking to trial AI.</p>

<p>ChatGPT, meanwhile, lets you pay monthly - around £20 per user per month. For organisations concerned about cashflow, or who are only looking to trial AI for a couple of months before committing, ChatGPT feels like the better investment.</p>

<p>Naturally, there are caveats. Of course, if you aren’t already in the Microsoft ecosystem, then this whole conversation is moot - between the two ChatGPT is the only logical choice. Equally, if the majority of your organisation spends most of its time on Teams calls and then writing up notes from those calls, then maybe you’ll benefit more from Copilot.</p>

<p>It’s also worth noting that, for all my personal experience, I have seen the technology work in live demos. Microsoft isn’t outright lying about Copilot’s capabilities. But these demos are in environments that have been specifically constructed to make the most of the AI tools. If you can get your organisation there, great! But if what you want is to dip your toe in the waters of AI to see how it might increase your org’s productivity, you aren’t going to want to first do a complete infrastructure overhaul to make that work.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>ChatGPT is a little bit better at a lot more things.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>At the end of the day, I find ChatGPT is more “generally” useful. There is pretty much nothing I’ve thrown at it in the last month or so that it hasn’t helped me with. From coding, to content structuring, to tidying up my CV. I’ve even thrown some very complicated data management queries at it, and where it can’t do it itself, it’s helped me write the scripts to get the job done. What it lacks in terms of interoperability with other tools, it makes up for in just being better at replying.</p>

<p>It’s also not just the accuracy of its responses. The <em>way</em> it responds to you feels more natural. Everything from the immediate response to the way it phrases answers feels more like you’re talking to a virtual personal assistant. There is just a lower barrier to entry for ChatGPT.</p>

<p>For the average organisation, the overlap between what ChatGPT and Copilot can both do is too high to justify both platforms. On balance, the option of monthly licenses, and that it is more of a general tool, swings me towards ChatGPT as the better option for starting your Generative AI journey.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="guides" /><category term="ai" /><category term="chatgpt" /><category term="copilot" /><category term="longread-2" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been using both ChatGPT4 and Microsoft Copilot for a couple of months. Weirdly, I couldn’t find a single post by anyone who had reviewed their experiences of it. So, I thought I’d throw in my two cents. ![Google Trends graph showing interest in the search term "Copilot vs ChatGPT" over the last 12 months. Graph shows a sharp increase in interest in the last 3 months.](images/copilot-chatgpt-google-trends-1024x402.png) Google Trends graph showing interest in the search term "Copilot vs ChatGPT" over the last 12 months. My main takeaway is that, as with a lot of technology, “which tool is better?” depends entirely on what you’re using it for. If you want the spoiler alert right up top, I end up deciding that, if you aren’t already embedded in Microsoft 365, for the average person ChatGPT will likely be the better call. There are quite a few caveats though, so do read on. For clarity’s sake, throughout I’m talking about OpenAI’s ChatGPT-4, and Microsoft’s Copilot for Microsoft 365. As well as some general observations about the benefits, I talk through two real-world tasks that I’ve done in the last month, to give a sense of where you might see the platforms limitations. Let’s dive in! Test 1: Working with Excel data Over at Esmée Fairbairn Foundation, we’re in the process of running a Youth Led Creativity Fund, and part of my work for that is to design and build the infrastructure behind it. Last week, this included allocating the 10 judges from our Involving Young People Collective to the 350-something applications we received for the fund. There are lots of ways one might choose to tackle this challenge. As the Technology Lead at the Foundation though, I’ve paid for a Copilot license to test out exactly what this can do. So I figured why do any real work myself? It’s a myth that getting AI means you don’t have to do any work. There are some stipulations to the allocations: Each application must be judged by two judges. We do not want to repeat judging pairs too often. And, as the final stipulation that you don’t have to tacitly acknowledge to humans, but you do to computers, a judge cannot assess the same application twice. I had all the applications in a spreadsheet, so Copilot seemed like the obvious play here. One of the major selling points of Copilot is that it sits right in your Microsoft 365 apps. So how did Microsoft’s Copilot do? So, here’s the prompt I ran for Copilot for Excel: In Table 1 there are 350 applications, each of which needs to be assessed by two judges. The names of the judges are in Table 2. Can you assign two judges to each application - using columns C and D - making sure that no judging pair is used more frequently than others, and that no judge assesses the same application twice? And so Copilot got to thinking. And then it did a bit more thinking. And then, for good measure, it thought some more. Finally, Copilot spits out an answer. Great! It can’t make any edits to the spreadsheet itself. Less great. But it will tell me what I need to do. That’s fine - giving me a formula is still taking some of the grunt work off me, so I’ll take it. What follows is a long answer about needed to create random numbers for each judge, and then using those numbers it can assign judges to each application. I don’t fully understand this, but that’s what I’m paying the AI for, so I do what it asks. The instructions themselves are relatively clear, though it’s still annoying that it can’t do any of this itself. I follow the instructions for both columns, and viola! It does it perfectly! For the first 10 applications. Then the spreadsheet throws up the dreaded #REF! error for each of the following 340-something. Not ideal. So, I plug my own brain back in and realise that it has assigned the 10 judges to the first 10 applications, but that the formula doesn’t account for the fact that the judges need to have more than 2 applications each. So, I go back to Copilot to explain the little misunderstanding. It offers some sincere apologies and then reworks the formula for me. Back and forth this goes for a little while, with none of the options working. I’m wasn’t getting anywhere, so eventually I simplified the problem. I didn’t need AI to assign both judges. Because each judge is assessing roughly the same number of applications, I can just use the old drag cell method to assign judges in repeating order for the first column. Once I’ve done that, I just need Copilot to assign the second judge. Surely that’s easier? Reader, it was not. Even after a few more exchanges, it kept giving me broken formulas. I don’t mean that the formulas gave me the wrong information. I mean that the syntax of the formula was incorrect. I know enough about Excel to work out where the formula didn’t work, so after a little manual effort I fixed it myself and ran it. But even when the formula gave an output, it was repeating judging pairs with almost perfect consistency. I went back to Copilot, gave it the fixed formula, and reminded it that I needed to mix up the judging pairs as much as possible. At that point, Copilot basically gave up, and offered me the start of a VBA script that might get me some of the way there. I’d spent nearly half an hour trying to get this to work, and it was rapidly becoming apparent that either I’m not good at prompt engineering, or Copilot just fundamentally wasn’t capable of providing what I needed. Now, clearly, I’m a fantastic prompt engineer, as those of you who have read my AI-generated Billy Joel homage will know. So I gave up on Copilot, and decided to see what ChatGPT could do… Using OpenAI’s ChatGPT Before I get into my experience with ChatGPT, there’s a very important point I need to make. While using Copilot, all of the data I was working with remained within my organisation’s infrastructure. Our Privacy Policy doesn’t yet mention anything about ChatGPT, so I didn’t have consent from either the applicants or the judges to upload their data to that third party. So, before I did anything, I needed to anonymise the data. This wasn’t difficult or particularly time-consuming, but I mention it for two reasons. One, it was another step I had to take, and that speaks to my point about AI not always being the quick and easy silver bullet. Two, it’s a very important step that a lot of organisations or individuals might not think to take. Anyway, with a new spreadsheet of anonymous information, I hit up ChatGPT with the following prompt. I have a spreadsheet of applications that I need to allocate judges to. I’ve already allocated the first judge, but I need to allocate a second one. Each application cannot be judged by the same person twice, and I want to minimise the number of times a judging pair is repeated. The spreadsheet has the allocations on a sheet called “Allocations”, and the Judge names on a sheet called “Judges”. Please can you fill out the “Judge 2” column on the allocations sheet with allocations. Again, at the risk of labouring the point, what I’d actually given it was a list of unique IDs pulled from our organisation’s CRM instead of the names of the applications, and a list of “Judge A, Judge B, Judge C….” instead of the names of the judges. This doesn’t matter to the AI - it’s just sorting data. But it gets me what I want (minus a little script work at the other end) without having to give the names of either organisations or people to a third party application. As you can see, I’d jumped straight into “easy mode”, giving ChatGPT the spreadsheet with Judge 1 already allocated. It made my life easier because a) I already had the sheet there, and b) it meant I had to think less hard about the prompt I was giving. ChatGPT responded immediately, saying: Certainly, I can help with that. Please upload the spreadsheet you mentioned. Once I have the file, I can analyze the existing allocations and propose a second judge for each application, ensuring that no application is judged by the same person twice and that judge pairs are not often repeated. What I liked about this response was that it was explaining back to me what it was going to do in very clear terms. It had understood what I needed. ChatGPT confirms what you’re asking of it, and then lets you know how it’s going to do it. So I uploaded my anonymised spreadsheet and let ChatGPT do its thing. It spent a lot of time analysing. To be fair to Copilot, ChatGPT took as long, if not slightly longer, to come back to me. I thought about giving a point to Microsoft for that but then remembered that the whole reason I was using ChatGPT was because Microsoft couldn’t do what I’d asked. I kept the point. Slightly less than an eon later (not quite 5 minutes), I got the following response: I have allocated a second judge to each application, ensuring that no judge is assigned to the same application twice and minimizing repeat judge pairings. You can download the updated spreadsheet using the link below: Yes, that’s right, not only had it done the calculations for me, but it had put it all into a nice new spreadsheet for me to download and use. Of course, I needed to go back in and un-anonymise the data again. But compared to manually allocating 10 judges to 350 applications, this seemed like a huge win. All told, including the time it took me to anonymise the table, write the prompt, wait for ChatGPT to do the work, un-anonymising the output, and lastly do some spot checks to make sure it had given me what I needed, no more than 15 minutes went by. The winner: ChatGPT (by a lot) I don’t know how long it would take me to have done this manually. I don’t mean manually-manually - adding 10 judges to 350 applications, making sure as few repeated pairs as possible would have taken me all day. What I mean is that I don’t know how I would have gone about that from a formula perspective. Before turning to AI, I had tried with PivotTables, but I didn’t get very far. I could have Googled it, I’m sure, or brought in one of my data colleagues. But Googling would have eaten into my day, with no immediate promise of success. And bringing in a colleague means taking up their time and capacity. The point of AI is to free up capacity in exactly this kind of way. And if that is the metric, then it’s clear that ChatGPT is the winner. Even if Copilot had given me the right formula, without too much fuss, it was still a comparatively manual process. As it was, I had to really work to get any output at all. With ChatGPT, I told it what I wanted, I gave it the data, and then I didn’t even have time to make myself a cup of tea before it had done the work for me. But this was a specific scenario that isn’t going to be something everyone does day-to-day. What about all the other stuff your average office worker might do? Copilot is built into your Microsoft environment Maybe my first use case was a little taxing for something that is still technically in preview. But one of the big selling points is that Copilot sits across your whole Microsoft organisation. There’s even a dedicated Copilot chat pinned to the top of your Teams application. Microsoft has been gearing up for this kind of integration for years. In fact, “AI” products have been part of the Office 365 platform for a while now. If you’ve ever used the PowerPoint designer tool, that is by a broad definition Generative AI. Even before Office 365, anyone who used Word in the late 90s and kept having to tell Clippy “No, I’m not writing a letter, get lost!” will know that we’ve had the power to do low-level AI-based generation for decades. ![Clippy, the late-90s "intelligent user interface" for Microsoft Word, asking whether the user needs help writing a letter.](images/Clippy-Letter.png) Clippy, who walked so Copilot could walk slightly faster. If I ignore my little issue with Excel - which again, to be fair, Microsoft does say is in Preview - there are dozens of other use cases where Copilot could make my life easier. With this in mind, I dove into the Teams chat function. I’d been having some back and forth with a colleague from finance about an upcoming audit. There was a particular document I wanted to get hold of, and I knew he’d emailed it to me a couple of weeks ago. I could have just searched Outlook, but everybody knows that’s a good way to lose 2 hours to fruitlessly rewording your search terms. I know it’s terrible practice to use Outlook as a repository for files. I know that as soon as I get an attachment that I know will be useful, I should load it up into SharePoint. I know that. You know that. But come on, who actually does that? Really? And besides, why can’t Microsoft just give us an email client that has good search functionality? Well, with Copilot, we don’t need one! I can ask it for something, and it will search the whole of my infrastructure to give me contextually useful information. Except, it can’t… When I asked Copilot in Teams to fetch me an email I knew that our auditors had sent us, it spent nearly 2 full minutes searching before it told me that it couldn’t find anything. I hopped over to Outlook and found the email in less than 30 seconds. Ok, so that’s not a win either. Maybe let’s give it a different type of task… Test 2: Planning my day Unlike the Excel problem, which I genuinely needed to get done and therefore have only really thought of as a head-to-head test retrospectively, for this I wanted to be a little more rigorous. We’ll see how that went… I gave both tools the same prompt: “Act as my personal assistant and help me plan my day. Here are the things I need to get done…” followed by a list of about 10 things, each with a rough amount of time for how long I thought it might take (“look into Microsoft Planner as an alternative to Jira - 40mins”, for example). Copilot has access to my calendar, whereas ChatGPT does not. Clearly, the advantage here, from a real-world use case scenario, should go to Microsoft. For Copilot, I added the line “The things already in my calendar are immovable”. For ChatGPT, I added “I also have the following meetings in my calendar:…” The results for both were… mixed… Copilot Copilot identified the commitments already in my calendar and worked around them. In the order that I’d given the tasks, it printed out a schedule that filled in the gaps around my meetings. When it got to 6pm, it told me that I could “…also use the time after 6 PM to complete the remaining tasks on [my] to-do list”. This, to me, seemed like a good result. I hadn’t specified any priorities, so it makes sense that it ran the schedule in the order I gave the tasks. Except… it didn’t put them into my calendar. When I followed up and explicitly asked it to do so, it told me that it was unable, and gave me instructions for how to do it myself. There seems to be a real hit-and-miss set of rules that dictate which parts of your environment Copilot can interact with directly. I understand it not being able to delete events, for example. What if it mistakenly deletes something important? But adding them surely can’t be a world-ending situation, can it Microsoft? I think this one irked me more because what is the point of a digital assistant if I still have to do most of the legwork? I use time-blocking quite a lot to manage my day. So by the time I’ve explained all of the tasks I have to Copilot, if it then needs me to put them in the Calendar myself the whole process is pointless. An AI assistant is only so useful, if you still have to do most of the legwork. To be honest, it annoyed me so much that I didn’t even bother trying to make changes to the prompt. I moved straight onto ChatGPT. So much for a rigorous head-to-head. ChatGPT Much like Copilot, ChatGPT gave me a breakdown of my day with tasks in the order I had given them. Unlike Copilot, it had formatted it nicely into morning, afternoon, and evening sections. ChatGPT had even put in a half-hour lunch break at midday, and 30 minutes at the end of the day to “Wrap up and review tasks for the day”. How nice of it. I suppose this was its way of directly responding to the “Act as my personal assistant” part of the prompt. And then things got weird. I followed up with the prompt “I also need to walk the dog for half an hour at some point this afternoon, can you fit that in?”. It had already put some of my meetings into the evening, lacking an apparent sense of work/life balance (adding lunch aside), I assumed it would just shove in “3.30-4pm: Dog walking” and move everything else back 30 mins. It’s what I would have done. It did not do that. In fact, in the Evening section, it provided me with the following: Morning: 10:30 - 11:00: All-hands meeting 11:00 - 12:00: Sort out email templates… 12:00 - 12:30: Lunch break Afternoon: 12:30 - 13:30: Call with… 13:30 - 14:00: Sort out… 14:00 - 14:15: Change address with… 14:15 - 14:45: Look into MS Planner as an alternative to Jira 14:45 - 15:25: Look at credits for Azure storage 15:25 - 15:35: Pay outstanding… 15:35 - 15:50: Check in with… 15:50 - 16:05: Pay… 16:05 - 16:20: Follow up on… 16:20 - 16:30: Wrap up and review tasks for the day Evening: 14:30 - 15:00: Walk the dog The formatting has been amended slightly, and some entries have been redacted. It had left the afternoon section untouched, leaving in the previous schedule across the 2.30pm-3pm slot. ChatGPT obviously understood that I needed 30 mins to walk the dog, and that it needed to be in the afternoon, as it assigned the 2.30-3pm time to it. But it then just tacked it onto the end of the day, rather than amend what else was going on. At first, I thought maybe ChatGPT had some kind of moral aversion to me running a personal errand in the middle of the afternoon. So I switched it. I gave it the follow-up prompt: “I’ve got a dog-walker now, so I don’t need to walk the dog. However, I now have a conference call that runs from 2.30pm to 3pm. Can you adjust my schedule?”. “Of course!” The answer immediately came back, before it gave me the same output but replacing “Walk the dog” with “Conference call” in the evening slot. I tried several different prompts, each as unsuccessful as the last. Eventually, I shut down that chat window and opened up a fresh one, giving it roughly the same initial prompt, but putting the conference call in from the start. It handled that mostly correctly, though it put the call in at the end of the day despite my telling it that it was fixed for 2.30pm. Once I clarified that though, it sent me back an amended schedule with no errors - though interestingly it no longer split it into Morning, Afternoon, and Evening segments. I even asked it to rearrange the tasks so that the Azure credits task was earlier in the day, and it amended the schedule fine. Just for giggles, I threw the dog walking question back in (“I forgot that I need to walk my dog for 30 mins this afternoon. Can you schedule that in?”), and it put that in for 3.30pm and arranged everything else around it. As a final test, I asked it to put it just after lunch instead. It put it in for the morning, but when I asked it to correct itself, it did. The winner: …no one? I liked that ChatGPT added in little things like a lunch break and time to wrap up at the end of the day. Most of the time, it looks like it can handle the task pretty well. However, from the looks of it if ChatGPT trips itself up it can be hard to put it back on track. As for Copilot… I struggled with this. I’ll come onto this more in a second, but from a financial point of view it is a larger commitment (you have to buy a one-year license). On top of that one of the major selling points is that it sits within your Microsoft infrastructure. But if it can’t add things to my calendar for me, what is the point? ChatGPT can’t do this either, but it doesn’t claim to be integrated. To be fair, this is perhaps a slightly contrived test scenario. So I thought a little more about how I would actually use a service like this. I opened up a new Copilot chat and gave it the prompt “Someone’s asked for a call at 3pm. Do I have time, and if so can you put a hold in my calendar.” 45 seconds later (yes, I timed it) it came back to tell me that I already had a call at 2pm that looked like it would run until 3.30, and therefore I would be unlikely to make the 3pm call. It also confirmed that, even if I had the time, it couldn’t put the hold in for me, as it was unable to add things to my calendar. I reset my stopwatch and then timed how long it took me to open up my Calendar, look at the 3pm slot, and then add a hold into that time anyway. 12 seconds. I also saw that in that time slot I had a conflicting meeting at 3pm anyway, which Copilot didn’t tell me about. ![Screenshot of Copilot response to the question "Do I have time for a call at 3pm, and can you put it in my calendar?" The response was that I have a call already, and that Copilot cannot add events into my calendar.](images/copilot-call-at-3pm.png) Screenshot of Copilot's response to a query about my availability for a call. So what is Copilot good for? I think, to be honest, the majority of the use I’ve got from Copilot is in summarising things. I get brought into long email threads relatively often, and instead of having to read through 30 emails to get a sense of what’s going on, a click of the Copilot button in Outlook gives me a decent summary to get started. Copilot really shines in Teams meetings. Similarly, one of the absolute best uses I’ve had for Copilot has been as an assistant in Teams meetings. If you record calls and enable transcripts, Copilot can offer real-time summaries of what’s being said, alongside citations and direct quotes. Once the meeting has ended, you can review summaries and action points, even splitting it out by person. If you were in an entirely Teams-based meeting - by which I mean everyone on the call has signed in, rather than a Hybrid situation where some of your team are together in a room and others are dialing in - you can see breakdowns of how much each person spoke, and click through visual representations of what was said when so you can see the recording for yourself. Of course, there are caveats to all of this. The first, and most obvious, is that you need to be having a Teams call for this to work. If your organisation isn’t already on Microsoft, this is going to be a big investment. Even if you have Microsoft 365, but tend to use Zoom, or Slack, to run your meetings, paying for Copilot might not be the smartest move. Incidentally, Zoom does have an equivalent AI meeting assistant, which gets very good reviews. It also comes included with every paid plan, compared to Copilot’s add-on fee. The second major caveat is that the call needs to be recorded, which means you’ll need permission from everyone on the call for that to be the case. This might well be fine for internal calls, but if you want to use Copilot to help you take notes on calls with clients, you’ll need to adjust your Privacy Policies. For someone in my position though, at an organisation that predominantly works with Microsoft products, Copilot for Teams is a game changer. I absolutely love it. For me, the summaries of the meetings alone are worth it, meaning you can pay less attention to note taking and be more present in the call. You can also query the notes after the fact, directly from the Teams app (“The meeting I had last Thursday about Data Privacy - what was Barry’s point about the cost-benefit of external providers?”). So which should I get? I so badly want to recommend Copilot. But while get a huge amount of value from Copilot for Teams, with regards to the rest of the platform… I don’t get the value of it as an AI chat assistant or as an omni-search for my organisation. I, personally, get zero value from it for PowerPoint and Excel (in fact it actively angers me for Excel). Word is a bit of a middle ground. I don’t get a lot of use from it, but I think that is in large part because that is where ChatGPT and Copilot overlap so obviously. As someone lucky enough to have subscriptions to both, I tend to default to ChatGPT. If I didn’t also have ChatGPT, I might get more out of Copilot for Word. Beyond that though, if I were offering a recommendation to a small/medium sized organisation, I think my overriding consideration is that you can only buy Copilot as a yearly license. Yes, the two platforms cost roughly the same when you consider them over a year, but you have to buy the full year with Copilot. At a cost of £300 per user, this might not be the right call for an organisation looking to trial AI. ChatGPT, meanwhile, lets you pay monthly - around £20 per user per month. For organisations concerned about cashflow, or who are only looking to trial AI for a couple of months before committing, ChatGPT feels like the better investment. Naturally, there are caveats. Of course, if you aren’t already in the Microsoft ecosystem, then this whole conversation is moot - between the two ChatGPT is the only logical choice. Equally, if the majority of your organisation spends most of its time on Teams calls and then writing up notes from those calls, then maybe you’ll benefit more from Copilot. It’s also worth noting that, for all my personal experience, I have seen the technology work in live demos. Microsoft isn’t outright lying about Copilot’s capabilities. But these demos are in environments that have been specifically constructed to make the most of the AI tools. If you can get your organisation there, great! But if what you want is to dip your toe in the waters of AI to see how it might increase your org’s productivity, you aren’t going to want to first do a complete infrastructure overhaul to make that work. ChatGPT is a little bit better at a lot more things. At the end of the day, I find ChatGPT is more “generally” useful. There is pretty much nothing I’ve thrown at it in the last month or so that it hasn’t helped me with. From coding, to content structuring, to tidying up my CV. I’ve even thrown some very complicated data management queries at it, and where it can’t do it itself, it’s helped me write the scripts to get the job done. What it lacks in terms of interoperability with other tools, it makes up for in just being better at replying. It’s also not just the accuracy of its responses. The way it responds to you feels more natural. Everything from the immediate response to the way it phrases answers feels more like you’re talking to a virtual personal assistant. There is just a lower barrier to entry for ChatGPT. For the average organisation, the overlap between what ChatGPT and Copilot can both do is too high to justify both platforms. On balance, the option of monthly licenses, and that it is more of a general tool, swings me towards ChatGPT as the better option for starting your Generative AI journey.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/chatGPTvsCopilot.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/chatGPTvsCopilot.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">No one is bad at tech</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/no-one-is-bad-a-tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No one is bad at tech" /><published>2024-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/no-one-is-bad-a-tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/no-one-is-bad-a-tech/"><![CDATA[<p>I popped into my local library the other day. I needed to print a delivery label for something, and I’d long since given up on owning a printer. I mean, why have a huge chunk of plastic taking up space, for the two times a year you need to print something, when it constantly thinks it’s out of ink, or needs its drivers replacing, takes and age to start up, never has the…</p>

<p>I’m digressing. Let’s start again…</p>

<p>I went to the library the other day to print something. It took me <strong><em>forever</em></strong>. Why? Was the library busy? Did the computers run slowly? Was there no one around to help with the infernally slow system?</p>

<p>Nope. None of that happened.</p>

<p>It took so long because I took so long. I couldn’t understand how the system worked. I’d have been out of there quicker if I’d asked any of the three staff around for help. But no, I am a tech expert (and also a stubborn man), so I did not ask for help. It’s just a networked printer for goodness’ sake. How hard could it be?</p>

<p>Anyway, 15 minutes later I gave in and asked for help. They couldn’t have been nicer when they showed me how absurdly easy everything was. They even pointed out that I didn’t need to use the library computer at all. If I connected my phone to the WiFi and scanned the QR code on the printer, I could print straight from my device.</p>

<p>I guess I have two points here.</p>

<p>The first is this: support your local library. They’re great. Your mileage is going to vary, but in my case, if I need to print something, I know it’ll cost me 20p and take less than 3 minutes. (Or at least, it will next time).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everyone struggles with technology. Everyone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My second point is this: everyone struggles with technology. Everyone. I’ve worked in tech for well over a decade. I’ve run technology transformation projects in hospitals. I’ve organised tech conferences, hackathons, and workshops across the country. I’ve been coding since I was 15 years old and have built dozens of websites from the ground up for just about every use case you could imagine. I currently manage the technology for one of the UK’s largest private foundations. And, it took me 20 minutes to print something at my local library. Everyone struggles with tech.</p>

<p>Not only does technology move so fast, but the requirements in any given case are so different. I set up the printing at my office, so in theory, I shouldn’t have had an issue. But the expectation on how that works is completely different. 40-something known people, printing from pre-approved devices, inside a private building, is a very different ask from a public building with potentially 100s of people a day needing to print from any number of devices. A pastry chef works in the kitchen, but they might not be the best person in the building to cook you a beef Wellington. (Note to self: rewatching The Bear always makes for better metaphors.)</p>

<p>To reiterate, there was nothing wrong with how the library was set up. It was intuitive, functioned quickly, and did exactly what I needed it to do. It was, with perhaps only a little hyperbole, perfect.</p>

<p>My issue was that I just wasn’t familiar with the system, and I immediately laid my assumptions of how it “should” work on top of it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Not all technology is built with all people in mind.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m certainly not bad when it comes to tech. But I think that’s my point - I don’t believe anyone is inherently bad at technology. It’s just that a lot of tech is designed only considering a certain type of mindset. I have that mindset. But when I encounter a system that is specifically built to account for people who aren’t nerds who don’t think in that way, I need to take a step back.</p>

<p>No one is inherently bad at technology. It’s just that not all technology is built to help all people equally. We need to get better at that.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="musings" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I popped into my local library the other day. I needed to print a delivery label for something, and I’d long since given up on owning a printer. I mean, why have a huge chunk of plastic taking up space, for the two times a year you need to print something, when it constantly thinks it’s out of ink, or needs its drivers replacing, takes and age to start up, never has the… I’m digressing. Let’s start again… I went to the library the other day to print something. It took me forever. Why? Was the library busy? Did the computers run slowly? Was there no one around to help with the infernally slow system? Nope. None of that happened. It took so long because I took so long. I couldn’t understand how the system worked. I’d have been out of there quicker if I’d asked any of the three staff around for help. But no, I am a tech expert (and also a stubborn man), so I did not ask for help. It’s just a networked printer for goodness’ sake. How hard could it be? Anyway, 15 minutes later I gave in and asked for help. They couldn’t have been nicer when they showed me how absurdly easy everything was. They even pointed out that I didn’t need to use the library computer at all. If I connected my phone to the WiFi and scanned the QR code on the printer, I could print straight from my device. I guess I have two points here. The first is this: support your local library. They’re great. Your mileage is going to vary, but in my case, if I need to print something, I know it’ll cost me 20p and take less than 3 minutes. (Or at least, it will next time). Everyone struggles with technology. Everyone. My second point is this: everyone struggles with technology. Everyone. I’ve worked in tech for well over a decade. I’ve run technology transformation projects in hospitals. I’ve organised tech conferences, hackathons, and workshops across the country. I’ve been coding since I was 15 years old and have built dozens of websites from the ground up for just about every use case you could imagine. I currently manage the technology for one of the UK’s largest private foundations. And, it took me 20 minutes to print something at my local library. Everyone struggles with tech. Not only does technology move so fast, but the requirements in any given case are so different. I set up the printing at my office, so in theory, I shouldn’t have had an issue. But the expectation on how that works is completely different. 40-something known people, printing from pre-approved devices, inside a private building, is a very different ask from a public building with potentially 100s of people a day needing to print from any number of devices. A pastry chef works in the kitchen, but they might not be the best person in the building to cook you a beef Wellington. (Note to self: rewatching The Bear always makes for better metaphors.) To reiterate, there was nothing wrong with how the library was set up. It was intuitive, functioned quickly, and did exactly what I needed it to do. It was, with perhaps only a little hyperbole, perfect. My issue was that I just wasn’t familiar with the system, and I immediately laid my assumptions of how it “should” work on top of it. Not all technology is built with all people in mind. I’m certainly not bad when it comes to tech. But I think that’s my point - I don’t believe anyone is inherently bad at technology. It’s just that a lot of tech is designed only considering a certain type of mindset. I have that mindset. But when I encounter a system that is specifically built to account for people who aren’t nerds who don’t think in that way, I need to take a step back. No one is inherently bad at technology. It’s just that not all technology is built to help all people equally. We need to get better at that.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog-jpg.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog-jpg.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">4 reasons I’m back on WordPress</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/4-reasons-im-back-on-wordpress/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4 reasons I’m back on WordPress" /><published>2024-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/4-reasons-im-back-on-wordpress</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/4-reasons-im-back-on-wordpress/"><![CDATA[<p>About four years ago, I spoke with great pride about <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/musings/i-blog-in-markdown-now/">moving my site from WordPress to Jekyll</a>. I wanted something fast, easy to update, and that didn’t require a whole lot from me.</p>

<p>Well, I’m back on WordPress now. Jekyll is fantastic, but here’s 4 reasons I’m glad I changed back.</p>

<h2 id="jekyll-wasnt-as-easy-to-post-as-i-wanted-it-to-be">Jekyll wasn’t as easy to post as I wanted it to be</h2>

<p>When I first moved over, my setup was a little different. I posted infrequently, and when I did, it was a considered and dedicated process of sitting in front of my laptop and Hemmingwaying my way through the drafts.</p>

<p>In a setup like that, where I have one device that I always write on, and one method that I always use, a tool like Jekyll makes sense.</p>

<p>But I’ve recently changed how I read, which in turn has changed how I write. For one thing, I might take me a couple of days to write a post, which means that I’ll be doing it over multiple devices, and I might want to finish and post from any of those devices. In this case, Jekyll presented some roadblocks. I procrastinate with writing at the best of times, so I need the process to be as frictionless as possible.</p>

<p>There are fixes and workarounds to this, of course. But when it gets to the point where your solution is more workaround than it is original platform, maybe it’s time to rethink.</p>

<p>Besides…</p>

<h2 id="gutenberg-is-fantastic">Gutenberg is fantastic</h2>

<p>Gutenberg - the wittly named built-in WordPress editor - has come on leaps and bounds in the last few updates. It’s go so advanced that I’m actually working with a client at the moment to migrate them from a professional theme builder plugin, to Gutenberg. Their end-users will have the exact same end-user, but faster, and the client will be able to manage their website without the overheads of another plugin.</p>

<p>In fact, for my own site, I had switched back to WordPress expecting to build my themes from code. Yes, because I’m a nerd. But also because I like the look of my site, I had the theme files already in Jekyll, and it wouldn’t have been too difficult to edit them for WordPress. In the end though, I didn’t bother. I built all each page from scratch in Gutenberg. All in an afternoon. It was that easy.</p>

<p>To be clear, there are use cases where you would want a theme builder. But, as an untested-but-educated-guess, I suspect that well over half the people using one could seriously consider switching to the baked-in version.</p>

<h2 id="i-can-still-write-in-markdown">I can still write in Markdown</h2>

<p>One of the big reasons I moved to Jekyll was actually nothing to do with Jekyll. It was because I had started writing everything in Markdown - a syntax that makes it really simple to write in a structured manner without much thought. Markdown was the driver, and Jekyll was the logical way to turn those Markdown files into a website.</p>

<p>But WordPress handles Markdown perfectly well. Whether you’re copy/pasting from a Markdown file into the editor, or you’re syncing from your writing tool (Obsidian) to your publishing tool (WordPress) you don’t need to worry about what the post will look like.</p>

<h2 id="some-things-are-just-easier-with-an-actual-interface">Some things are just easier with an actual interface</h2>

<p>Markdown is great for a lot of things - including adding 95% of the styling you want to your text. Sometimes though, having an editor makes things so much easier.</p>

<p>Images are probably the thing that was the most “extra work” on Jekyll. With WordPress, I add it straight to where I want it (most often as the header image to the post) and the site will do the upload, compress the file, and make sure it’s in the right place. Each of those steps was a manual process before. It wasn’t arduous at all, but again, I’m very good at procrastinating on blogs.</p>

<h1 id="so-what-does-my-writing-process-look-like-now">So what does my writing process look like now?</h1>

<p>Typically, something like this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Read something interesting, and decide I want to opine. This will usually happen in Omnivore, and maybe I’ll have taken some notes within the platform.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Often now, I’ll actually dictate the first draft of my posts, rather than write them. I do this on my phone while I’m walking the dog, and copy/paste the automated transcript straight into Obsidian to carry on editing. Either way, Obsidian is where I engage the keyboard part of the process. If I’ve take notes in Omnivore, I’ll pull them from a synced folder in Obsidian. Otherwise I’ll just start writing.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Depending on the topic, it might take me a couple of days to write the post. Obsidian syncs across all my devices, so I can pick it up and write anytime on any device.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>When I’m 90% happy with the post, I have a button in Obsidian that sends it to WordPress, as an unpublished draft.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Opening up WordPress (again, from any device), I can make final edits - including stylistic things like adding images, or pullquotes. I’ll also add in the metadata bits, like the category and tags, and the excerpt.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I’ll hit publish, and I’m done!</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h1 id="i-will-miss-jekyll-but-it-was-the-right-move">I will miss Jekyll, but it was the right move</h1>

<p>I still love Jekyll, and it will always be a tool I consider when approaching new web-based projects. It’s fast, very customisable, and of course Free and Open Source. And, as I alluded to right at the top, if there was something you wanted Jekyll to do, there was almost certainly a way to make it work.</p>

<p>As a nice little cherry on top, using a free GitHub account, and the free Jekyll software, you can run a great looking site for free. All you have to pay for, if you want it, is a custom domain name. Apart from that, it is (and I don’t know if I mentioned this), free.</p>

<p>Beyond all that, it’s undeniable that the WordPress site is slower to run. From an actual perfect PageSpeed insights score more or less out of the box, to currently sitting in the low 90s for desktop and mid 60s for mobile, there’s definitely more work I need to do to this WordPress site before I’m happy.</p>

<p>On the flipside, I switched the site over last weekend, and I’ve already posted 3 new things. I already had a hosting provider - of course I did, I’m a web dev - but like Jekyll you can host a WordPress website site from as little as £0 on their servers. Or get your own for a few pounds a month if you want better customisation. There’s a very good reason it’s the world’s most popular content management system.</p>

<p>I’m glad I went through my Jekyll phase. And I’ve no doubt I’ll go back to it for something at some point.</p>

<p>But I’m also glad to be back on WordPress.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="musings" /><category term="web-development" /><category term="wordpress" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[About four years ago, I spoke with great pride about moving my site from WordPress to Jekyll. I wanted something fast, easy to update, and that didn’t require a whole lot from me. Well, I’m back on WordPress now. Jekyll is fantastic, but here’s 4 reasons I’m glad I changed back. Jekyll wasn’t as easy to post as I wanted it to be When I first moved over, my setup was a little different. I posted infrequently, and when I did, it was a considered and dedicated process of sitting in front of my laptop and Hemmingwaying my way through the drafts. In a setup like that, where I have one device that I always write on, and one method that I always use, a tool like Jekyll makes sense. But I’ve recently changed how I read, which in turn has changed how I write. For one thing, I might take me a couple of days to write a post, which means that I’ll be doing it over multiple devices, and I might want to finish and post from any of those devices. In this case, Jekyll presented some roadblocks. I procrastinate with writing at the best of times, so I need the process to be as frictionless as possible. There are fixes and workarounds to this, of course. But when it gets to the point where your solution is more workaround than it is original platform, maybe it’s time to rethink. Besides… Gutenberg is fantastic Gutenberg - the wittly named built-in WordPress editor - has come on leaps and bounds in the last few updates. It’s go so advanced that I’m actually working with a client at the moment to migrate them from a professional theme builder plugin, to Gutenberg. Their end-users will have the exact same end-user, but faster, and the client will be able to manage their website without the overheads of another plugin. In fact, for my own site, I had switched back to WordPress expecting to build my themes from code. Yes, because I’m a nerd. But also because I like the look of my site, I had the theme files already in Jekyll, and it wouldn’t have been too difficult to edit them for WordPress. In the end though, I didn’t bother. I built all each page from scratch in Gutenberg. All in an afternoon. It was that easy. To be clear, there are use cases where you would want a theme builder. But, as an untested-but-educated-guess, I suspect that well over half the people using one could seriously consider switching to the baked-in version. I can still write in Markdown One of the big reasons I moved to Jekyll was actually nothing to do with Jekyll. It was because I had started writing everything in Markdown - a syntax that makes it really simple to write in a structured manner without much thought. Markdown was the driver, and Jekyll was the logical way to turn those Markdown files into a website. But WordPress handles Markdown perfectly well. Whether you’re copy/pasting from a Markdown file into the editor, or you’re syncing from your writing tool (Obsidian) to your publishing tool (WordPress) you don’t need to worry about what the post will look like. Some things are just easier with an actual interface Markdown is great for a lot of things - including adding 95% of the styling you want to your text. Sometimes though, having an editor makes things so much easier. Images are probably the thing that was the most “extra work” on Jekyll. With WordPress, I add it straight to where I want it (most often as the header image to the post) and the site will do the upload, compress the file, and make sure it’s in the right place. Each of those steps was a manual process before. It wasn’t arduous at all, but again, I’m very good at procrastinating on blogs. So what does my writing process look like now? Typically, something like this: Read something interesting, and decide I want to opine. This will usually happen in Omnivore, and maybe I’ll have taken some notes within the platform. Often now, I’ll actually dictate the first draft of my posts, rather than write them. I do this on my phone while I’m walking the dog, and copy/paste the automated transcript straight into Obsidian to carry on editing. Either way, Obsidian is where I engage the keyboard part of the process. If I’ve take notes in Omnivore, I’ll pull them from a synced folder in Obsidian. Otherwise I’ll just start writing. Depending on the topic, it might take me a couple of days to write the post. Obsidian syncs across all my devices, so I can pick it up and write anytime on any device. When I’m 90% happy with the post, I have a button in Obsidian that sends it to WordPress, as an unpublished draft. Opening up WordPress (again, from any device), I can make final edits - including stylistic things like adding images, or pullquotes. I’ll also add in the metadata bits, like the category and tags, and the excerpt. I’ll hit publish, and I’m done! I will miss Jekyll, but it was the right move I still love Jekyll, and it will always be a tool I consider when approaching new web-based projects. It’s fast, very customisable, and of course Free and Open Source. And, as I alluded to right at the top, if there was something you wanted Jekyll to do, there was almost certainly a way to make it work. As a nice little cherry on top, using a free GitHub account, and the free Jekyll software, you can run a great looking site for free. All you have to pay for, if you want it, is a custom domain name. Apart from that, it is (and I don’t know if I mentioned this), free. Beyond all that, it’s undeniable that the WordPress site is slower to run. From an actual perfect PageSpeed insights score more or less out of the box, to currently sitting in the low 90s for desktop and mid 60s for mobile, there’s definitely more work I need to do to this WordPress site before I’m happy. On the flipside, I switched the site over last weekend, and I’ve already posted 3 new things. I already had a hosting provider - of course I did, I’m a web dev - but like Jekyll you can host a WordPress website site from as little as £0 on their servers. Or get your own for a few pounds a month if you want better customisation. There’s a very good reason it’s the world’s most popular content management system. I’m glad I went through my Jekyll phase. And I’ve no doubt I’ll go back to it for something at some point. But I’m also glad to be back on WordPress.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog-jpg.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog-jpg.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RSS: Why I think it’s overdue a comeback</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/rss-why-i-think-its-overdue-a-comeback/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RSS: Why I think it’s overdue a comeback" /><published>2024-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/rss-why-i-think-its-overdue-a-comeback</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/rss-why-i-think-its-overdue-a-comeback/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been thinking a lot about RSS lately. I know, I know. My last post was about the emerging super-tech that is generative AI. And here I am thinking about technology that predates the original iPad. By a decade. But you heard it here first: RSS is making a comeback! We’re hearing more and more about ChatGPT, Co-Pilot, Gemini, and the others. But I’ve also been hearing more and more people talk about RSS. Even the guys over on the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/01/26/podcasts/hard-fork-ai-news-media-a16z-chris-dixon.html">Hard Fork podcast</a> have been chatting about it.</p>

<p>For me, the two things are related - the more we’re talking about the new and shiny AI tools, the more we’re also talking about some of the early building blocks of the web.</p>

<p>So, what is RSS? Where did it go? And why is it coming back? Well friends, grab yourself a cup of tea and settle in…</p>

<h1 id="what-is-rss-a-quick-intro">What is RSS: a quick intro</h1>

<p>RSS (“really simple syndication”) is a text-based, machine-readable, web feed. It’s essentially a way of tracking when a particular source has posted something new. In the early days of the internet, the World Wide Web was just that - a web of barely connected websites, from blogs, forums, news pages, webcomics, you name it. And if you wanted to keep up to date on everything, you needed to visit each of those places individually to find out what was happening. You “surfed the web”, if you will.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You used to have to “surf the web” because there was no easy way to bring together the things you wanted to see.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Then, in 1999, RSS came along. It gave us a way for websites to let users know when there was an update. Instead of going to your favourite blogger’s website every morning when you got to work and keeping your fingers crossed, you’d fire up your RSS Reader and get a list of the latest from across your web.</p>

<p>This was a game-changer. With an RSS Reader, you could amalgamate everything you wanted to check out from different pockets of the internet. If that sounds like a familiar concept to you, that’s because the way we use the web hasn’t really changed since then. The main difference is that today, instead of RSS feeds, we use social media. One social media platform above others has taken on the mantle of spiritual successor to our good friend RSS: Twitter.</p>

<h1 id="where-did-rss-go">Where did RSS go?</h1>

<p>While Twitter was never the most popular social media platform by number of users - that honour goes to Facebook - it had something none of the others had. The brevity of posts, the ability to follow anyone, and the vast mix of noraml people, celebrities, organisations, and news outlets, meant it really was the only place you needed if you wanted to curate your sources of knowledge. People who had blogs would let their Twitter followers know when they posted. News outlets would post breaking stories on Twitter. Pop stars would annouce their latest albums. If you wanted to update the wider world about something, you headed over to let that little blue bird know.</p>

<p>It had the upsides of RSS - ease of use, and all your favourite things in one place. But it also had RSS beat in one very big way. RSS is a one-way street. Twitter gave you the ability to talk back. To anybody. About anything. Communication was never the same again.</p>

<p>The late 2000s / early 2010s saw a steady decline in RSS. In 2013, Google shutdown it’s RSS Reader, signaling to many that the age of RSS had officially ended. The technology still lived on, of course. In fact, even today if you subscribe to any podcasts, it’s RSS that lets your app know when a new episode is live. And most publications and blogs still have RSS feeds built into them - apps like Feedly and Omnivore will make use of them for you. But it’s no longer part of the mainstream vernacular of the internet.</p>

<p>I think that might change.</p>

<h1 id="what-might-cause-the-renairssance">What might cause the renaiRSSance</h1>

<p>Alright, that one was a stretch…</p>

<p>For all its lack of two-way communication, or fancy hashtagging, you know one thing RSS never did? It never showed you anything you hadn’t subscribed to. As social media platforms needed to capture more users and drive more traffic, they implemented algorithms. These bits of code learned what you shared, made notes of what the people you followed liked, and ultimately started to change what you saw on your feed. Platforms included adverts and promoted posts. They showed you things that people outside your internet circle thought were popular. As time went on, less and less of your feed was things that you had originally signed up to follow.</p>

<p>For some people in some contexts, this is fine. Better than fine in fact. TikTok pretty much operates on the basis that its users want to see new, popular, trending things, regardless of who it’s from. In other corners of the internet though, this isn’t what people signed up for. Elon Musk was the final straw for Twitter, but usage was declining long before that.</p>

<p>People are still consuming content at increasing rates though. By the time NPR left X, the news outlet reported a <a href="https://niemanreports.org/articles/npr-twitter-musk/">negligible decline</a> in visitors to their site. It didn’t matter that they’d gone, because people had already been getting their NPR updates from another medium. A large part of their traffic had long been coming from - you guessed it! RS- nah I’m kidding. It was newsletters.</p>

<p>Newsletters, in fact, have been doing remarkably well. Back in 2022, Reuters reported that <a href="https://reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk/journalism-media-and-technology-trends-and-predictions-2022">70% of the publishers</a> they surveyed were putting more resources into newsletters than other platforms. They were betting big on email, and pulling funding from “traditional” social media. Why is that, I wonder? What is it about subscribing to a specific publication, and getting the updates from that publication all in one place, that you can peruse at your leisure?</p>

<h1 id="so-newsletters-are-the-way-forward-not-rss">So newsletters are the way forward, not RSS?</h1>

<p>Maybe. But I think newsletters are only a small part of the puzzle.</p>

<p>People want more control over the content they consume. Newsletters give that, but there are still hurdles. From the content creator side, there’s no shortage of platforms you can use to run a newsletter business. But as with many things tech, these platforms themselves come under scrutiny. Substack, perhaps the best-known platform, <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2023/11/substack-extremism-nazi-white-supremacy-newsletters/676156/">hit the headlines late last year</a> for all the wrong reasons when it refused to take down the newsletters of actual neo-Nazis. They later backtracked (<a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/1/8/24030756/substack-nazi-newsletter-content-moderation">sort of…</a>), but the whole affair caused a lot of discussion in the space about where content creators should go to host their content. What was wrong, some asked, with the good old-fashioned website?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We want more control over the content we consume. Social media isn’t giving us that.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I also think there is a space for content consumption outside of our email inboxes. I’ve <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/articles/ive-recently-changed-how-i-consume-content/">talked before</a> about how I use Omnivore and RSS to get my news. I’m a nerd, and not representative of the population at large. However, I think there is something to be said for a completely curated feed, free of algorithmic influence, and separate from the systems we have to use for work. For about 5 minutes, I thought <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/musings/yes-im-on-mastodon-now-too/">Mastodon might be the answer</a>. But the social media landscape is now far too fragmented. Between Mastodon, and BlueSky, and Threads, and X, and the half dozen others that will have popped up in the time it’s taken me to write this post, it’s just not a streamlined way for someone producing content to reach a wide audience.</p>

<p>So, I’m setting my stall out. I think we’ll see the comeback of RSS. It’s not the solution we deserve, but it’s the one we need right now.</p>

<p>Oh, and if you want the RSS feed for this blog, you can point your readers to: <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/feed/">https://willrc.co.uk/feed/</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinions" /><category term="communication" /><category term="internet" /><category term="rss" /><category term="social-media" /><category term="twitter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been thinking a lot about RSS lately. I know, I know. My last post was about the emerging super-tech that is generative AI. And here I am thinking about technology that predates the original iPad. By a decade. But you heard it here first: RSS is making a comeback! We’re hearing more and more about ChatGPT, Co-Pilot, Gemini, and the others. But I’ve also been hearing more and more people talk about RSS. Even the guys over on the Hard Fork podcast have been chatting about it. For me, the two things are related - the more we’re talking about the new and shiny AI tools, the more we’re also talking about some of the early building blocks of the web. So, what is RSS? Where did it go? And why is it coming back? Well friends, grab yourself a cup of tea and settle in… What is RSS: a quick intro RSS (“really simple syndication”) is a text-based, machine-readable, web feed. It’s essentially a way of tracking when a particular source has posted something new. In the early days of the internet, the World Wide Web was just that - a web of barely connected websites, from blogs, forums, news pages, webcomics, you name it. And if you wanted to keep up to date on everything, you needed to visit each of those places individually to find out what was happening. You “surfed the web”, if you will. You used to have to “surf the web” because there was no easy way to bring together the things you wanted to see. Then, in 1999, RSS came along. It gave us a way for websites to let users know when there was an update. Instead of going to your favourite blogger’s website every morning when you got to work and keeping your fingers crossed, you’d fire up your RSS Reader and get a list of the latest from across your web. This was a game-changer. With an RSS Reader, you could amalgamate everything you wanted to check out from different pockets of the internet. If that sounds like a familiar concept to you, that’s because the way we use the web hasn’t really changed since then. The main difference is that today, instead of RSS feeds, we use social media. One social media platform above others has taken on the mantle of spiritual successor to our good friend RSS: Twitter. Where did RSS go? While Twitter was never the most popular social media platform by number of users - that honour goes to Facebook - it had something none of the others had. The brevity of posts, the ability to follow anyone, and the vast mix of noraml people, celebrities, organisations, and news outlets, meant it really was the only place you needed if you wanted to curate your sources of knowledge. People who had blogs would let their Twitter followers know when they posted. News outlets would post breaking stories on Twitter. Pop stars would annouce their latest albums. If you wanted to update the wider world about something, you headed over to let that little blue bird know. It had the upsides of RSS - ease of use, and all your favourite things in one place. But it also had RSS beat in one very big way. RSS is a one-way street. Twitter gave you the ability to talk back. To anybody. About anything. Communication was never the same again. The late 2000s / early 2010s saw a steady decline in RSS. In 2013, Google shutdown it’s RSS Reader, signaling to many that the age of RSS had officially ended. The technology still lived on, of course. In fact, even today if you subscribe to any podcasts, it’s RSS that lets your app know when a new episode is live. And most publications and blogs still have RSS feeds built into them - apps like Feedly and Omnivore will make use of them for you. But it’s no longer part of the mainstream vernacular of the internet. I think that might change. What might cause the renaiRSSance Alright, that one was a stretch… For all its lack of two-way communication, or fancy hashtagging, you know one thing RSS never did? It never showed you anything you hadn’t subscribed to. As social media platforms needed to capture more users and drive more traffic, they implemented algorithms. These bits of code learned what you shared, made notes of what the people you followed liked, and ultimately started to change what you saw on your feed. Platforms included adverts and promoted posts. They showed you things that people outside your internet circle thought were popular. As time went on, less and less of your feed was things that you had originally signed up to follow. For some people in some contexts, this is fine. Better than fine in fact. TikTok pretty much operates on the basis that its users want to see new, popular, trending things, regardless of who it’s from. In other corners of the internet though, this isn’t what people signed up for. Elon Musk was the final straw for Twitter, but usage was declining long before that. People are still consuming content at increasing rates though. By the time NPR left X, the news outlet reported a negligible decline in visitors to their site. It didn’t matter that they’d gone, because people had already been getting their NPR updates from another medium. A large part of their traffic had long been coming from - you guessed it! RS- nah I’m kidding. It was newsletters. Newsletters, in fact, have been doing remarkably well. Back in 2022, Reuters reported that 70% of the publishers they surveyed were putting more resources into newsletters than other platforms. They were betting big on email, and pulling funding from “traditional” social media. Why is that, I wonder? What is it about subscribing to a specific publication, and getting the updates from that publication all in one place, that you can peruse at your leisure? So newsletters are the way forward, not RSS? Maybe. But I think newsletters are only a small part of the puzzle. People want more control over the content they consume. Newsletters give that, but there are still hurdles. From the content creator side, there’s no shortage of platforms you can use to run a newsletter business. But as with many things tech, these platforms themselves come under scrutiny. Substack, perhaps the best-known platform, hit the headlines late last year for all the wrong reasons when it refused to take down the newsletters of actual neo-Nazis. They later backtracked (sort of…), but the whole affair caused a lot of discussion in the space about where content creators should go to host their content. What was wrong, some asked, with the good old-fashioned website? We want more control over the content we consume. Social media isn’t giving us that. I also think there is a space for content consumption outside of our email inboxes. I’ve talked before about how I use Omnivore and RSS to get my news. I’m a nerd, and not representative of the population at large. However, I think there is something to be said for a completely curated feed, free of algorithmic influence, and separate from the systems we have to use for work. For about 5 minutes, I thought Mastodon might be the answer. But the social media landscape is now far too fragmented. Between Mastodon, and BlueSky, and Threads, and X, and the half dozen others that will have popped up in the time it’s taken me to write this post, it’s just not a streamlined way for someone producing content to reach a wide audience. So, I’m setting my stall out. I think we’ll see the comeback of RSS. It’s not the solution we deserve, but it’s the one we need right now. Oh, and if you want the RSS feed for this blog, you can point your readers to: https://willrc.co.uk/feed/]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/wherda-arsianto-l7dP0O8Dj60-unsplash-scaled.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/wherda-arsianto-l7dP0O8Dj60-unsplash-scaled.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Some thoughts on AI</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/some-thoughts-on-ai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some thoughts on AI" /><published>2024-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/some-thoughts-on-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/some-thoughts-on-ai/"><![CDATA[<p>ChatGPT has been around for a little while. Lately though, we’ve had some other big players join the “Generative AI” arena. Perhaps most notable is Microsoft making their Copilot considerably easier to access. For about £25 a month, you get Microsoft’s range of AI tools.</p>

<p>So, what does this mean for the current state of play for Generative Artificial Intelligence? Who is using it, and what are they using it for? Perhaps most importantly, is it worth getting?</p>

<p>Let’s find out.</p>

<h1 id="what-are-we-using-ai-for">What are we using AI for?</h1>

<p>In a survey of over 140 IT Leaders, The Channel Company (parent company for, among other publications, Computing.com) found that 76% of respondents use AI for Data Analytics. Additionally, 60% said they used AI Assistants, and 40% used AI for Natural Language Processing.</p>

<p>What is interesting to me is that none of these things are groundbreaking. We’ve had Machine Learning helping us with data analysis for decades, and AI Assistants have been accessible to the masses in various forms since the first iPhone. Don’t get me wrong. The quality of the work from today’s AI is streets ahead of where it used to be. The idea that 2011 Siri would do anything useful is laughable. But sci-fi of old promised us a redefined society: a flying-car filled utopia. When are we getting that?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What we’re using AI for isn’t groundbreaking - but it’s reach is about to be.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We’re a little way off yet. But what is happening is still hugely beneficial, and we’re only just figuring out how the “average” person can use it.</p>

<p>Let’s look at Microsoft Copilot again. One of the things it advertises is a better way to attend meetings. You can join a Teams call with your colleagues and have Copilot “sit in” taking notes. At the end of the meeting, you’ll almost instantly have a transcript of what was said by whom. But no one’s got time to read a transcript to understand what went on, so you’ll also get a summary, distilled into 5 or 6 bullet points, as well as any action points from the meeting. That’s easily an hour of someone’s time post-meeting that they can get back.</p>

<p>What else? Let’s say you’ve got to run through the results of a 300-person survey. You’ve got to collate all that data, put it into a two-page report for your Senior Management Team, <em>and</em> you also need to produce a 5-slide presentation to give at the next all-hands meeting. How long are you going to block out to do that? A couple of hours? Half a day? A full day? Seems long. And besides, no one has a full day to put aside for this kind of work, so you’re going to have to split that time out across three weeks’ worth of 2 hours here and 40 minutes there. It’s going be draining having to switch back and forth, and it’ll likely push back other timelines that you’re working on.</p>

<p>That seems like a waste of everyone’s time. Now, you can get Copilot to do all that in a matter of minutes, and you only spend half an hour checking it over and making some light edits.</p>

<p>This sort of thing is going to become really popular, really quickly. A lot of people already have a Microsoft 365 license, so adding this feature on for - as all the marketing will remind you - about £1 a day seems like a no-brainer. It’s also a much simpler sell for companies compared to, for example, ChatGPT. Copilot is ChatGPT with bells on, but those bells integrate it directly with your email, your calendar, with PowerPoint, with…</p>

<p>Because of the price point, companies will quickly see a return on spending. It’s hard to get figures on exactly what this looks like. But even if Microsoft’s claim that you can “<a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2023/03/16/introducing-microsoft-365-copilot-your-copilot-for-work/">clear your inbox in minutes, not hours</a>” is the only thing the tool does, and you spend <a href="https://hbr.org/2019/01/how-to-spend-way-less-time-on-email-every-day">two hours a day on emails</a>, then suddenly £25 buys me nearly 3 days a month back. And that’s without the other bells and whistles Microsoft tells me Copilot can do. With that time, I can start to work on more strategic work.</p>

<p><em>To work that out, I assumed that Copilot could cut down my emailing from 2 hours to 1 hour a day. I assumed a 5-day working week, meaning 5 hours saved over a week. With an average of 4 weeks in a month, that’s 20 hours saved. If a work day lasts 8 hours, then overall I get 2.5 days back just by saving 1 hour a day of email time.</em></p>

<h1 id="but-will-ai-take-my-job">But will AI take my job?</h1>

<p>Am I worried about jobs? Only a little. As someone who has been a web developer for the last decade and a half, I liken the rise in Generative AI to the popularity of platforms like Squarespace.</p>

<p>Squarespace leveled the playing field when it came to building websites. It’s a great piece of kit for anyone who wants to build a small portfolio website, a blog, a modest online store, etc. If you want a site, you want it done, and you want as little fuss as possible - have at it. Spend a couple of hours getting the look right - you don’t need to spin up servers, you don’t need to configure WordPress or install plugins. £10/month, job done. It’s fantastic - and I say that as someone who makes money doing the same thing that you can pay Squarespace to do.</p>

<p>Except I don’t - and that’s the point. Squarespace isn’t going to help you if you need a completely stand-out website. It’s not the right tool for you if you want a bespoke CMS for your publication. It’s going to struggle if you need a high-traffic, multi-seller, international e-commerce platform. You can’t use it if you have specific data security requirements. Squarespace isn’t designed to help in those cases. In those scenarios, and hundreds more, you need a web developer. (<a href="https://willrc.co.uk/services/">Hello, by the way!</a> 👋)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Generative AI is like Squarespace - a great tool for a simple and specific need.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t believe I’ve lost significant business because Squarespace exists. I also think that thousands more people have an accessible online voice because of the likes of Squarespace, people who wouldn’t have been able to have one without it.</p>

<p>In the same vein, I don’t believe this wave of AI will result in millions of 9-5 “office worker” jobs lost. There are things it just isn’t designed to do. There was a period where we all got caught up in the hype that AI would solve everything, and we’d be able to kick back in our utopia while the robots did all the work. Maybe that’s coming, but not yet. Not soon. And that’s OK - technology isn’t really supposed to be a broad-brush solution to all problems. Specific interventions need to be specifically deployed to get the best out of it. That’s where I believe we’re at. We are going to see an exponential rise in the number of people using Generative AI, in a much smaller number of use cases.</p>

<p>I think that’s going to be really exciting. The low-hanging fruit, the easy return on investment stuff, will be more widely used. It’s will really open up how people can spend their time - not just physical hours, but also the mental capacity to think about more important things.</p>

<h1 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h1>

<p>It’s quite the rosy picture I’ve painted! Don’t misunderstand me, I know there are still hurdles to jump. There are ethical considerations, climate change factors, and myriad data concerns surrounding AI that I’ve not explored here. In the coming weeks and months, I will break these down. Watch this space.</p>

<p>I also know that there are likely to be cases of some jobs being replaced, despite my sunny optimism. But in the round, I think we’re less likely to see entire jobs being taken over by machines, and instead have individual people be “augmented” in specific ways, giving them back time and capacity.</p>

<p>I work predominately in the charity and social sector. It’s a space where it’s common for any given person to be doing the work of four people. I’m excited for a world where it’s accessible - both in terms of price and ease of use - for people in the space to only do the work of three people. <em>Maybe even only two.</em></p>

<p>I jest (sort of). But it is a real possibility. Small organisations can’t afford to hire extra people, and AI isn’t able to replace existing ones. But, perhaps for the first time, we have a genuinely viable third option, where for a little extra money we might get a lot more out. It will help people redefine what their work is, and to spend their time doing more meaningful work.</p>

<p>So that’s where I think we are. And I am excited.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinions" /><category term="ai" /><category term="chatgpt" /><category term="copilot" /><category term="internet" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChatGPT has been around for a little while. Lately though, we’ve had some other big players join the “Generative AI” arena. Perhaps most notable is Microsoft making their Copilot considerably easier to access. For about £25 a month, you get Microsoft’s range of AI tools. So, what does this mean for the current state of play for Generative Artificial Intelligence? Who is using it, and what are they using it for? Perhaps most importantly, is it worth getting? Let’s find out. What are we using AI for? In a survey of over 140 IT Leaders, The Channel Company (parent company for, among other publications, Computing.com) found that 76% of respondents use AI for Data Analytics. Additionally, 60% said they used AI Assistants, and 40% used AI for Natural Language Processing. What is interesting to me is that none of these things are groundbreaking. We’ve had Machine Learning helping us with data analysis for decades, and AI Assistants have been accessible to the masses in various forms since the first iPhone. Don’t get me wrong. The quality of the work from today’s AI is streets ahead of where it used to be. The idea that 2011 Siri would do anything useful is laughable. But sci-fi of old promised us a redefined society: a flying-car filled utopia. When are we getting that? What we’re using AI for isn’t groundbreaking - but it’s reach is about to be. We’re a little way off yet. But what is happening is still hugely beneficial, and we’re only just figuring out how the “average” person can use it. Let’s look at Microsoft Copilot again. One of the things it advertises is a better way to attend meetings. You can join a Teams call with your colleagues and have Copilot “sit in” taking notes. At the end of the meeting, you’ll almost instantly have a transcript of what was said by whom. But no one’s got time to read a transcript to understand what went on, so you’ll also get a summary, distilled into 5 or 6 bullet points, as well as any action points from the meeting. That’s easily an hour of someone’s time post-meeting that they can get back. What else? Let’s say you’ve got to run through the results of a 300-person survey. You’ve got to collate all that data, put it into a two-page report for your Senior Management Team, and you also need to produce a 5-slide presentation to give at the next all-hands meeting. How long are you going to block out to do that? A couple of hours? Half a day? A full day? Seems long. And besides, no one has a full day to put aside for this kind of work, so you’re going to have to split that time out across three weeks’ worth of 2 hours here and 40 minutes there. It’s going be draining having to switch back and forth, and it’ll likely push back other timelines that you’re working on. That seems like a waste of everyone’s time. Now, you can get Copilot to do all that in a matter of minutes, and you only spend half an hour checking it over and making some light edits. This sort of thing is going to become really popular, really quickly. A lot of people already have a Microsoft 365 license, so adding this feature on for - as all the marketing will remind you - about £1 a day seems like a no-brainer. It’s also a much simpler sell for companies compared to, for example, ChatGPT. Copilot is ChatGPT with bells on, but those bells integrate it directly with your email, your calendar, with PowerPoint, with… Because of the price point, companies will quickly see a return on spending. It’s hard to get figures on exactly what this looks like. But even if Microsoft’s claim that you can “clear your inbox in minutes, not hours” is the only thing the tool does, and you spend two hours a day on emails, then suddenly £25 buys me nearly 3 days a month back. And that’s without the other bells and whistles Microsoft tells me Copilot can do. With that time, I can start to work on more strategic work. To work that out, I assumed that Copilot could cut down my emailing from 2 hours to 1 hour a day. I assumed a 5-day working week, meaning 5 hours saved over a week. With an average of 4 weeks in a month, that’s 20 hours saved. If a work day lasts 8 hours, then overall I get 2.5 days back just by saving 1 hour a day of email time. But will AI take my job? Am I worried about jobs? Only a little. As someone who has been a web developer for the last decade and a half, I liken the rise in Generative AI to the popularity of platforms like Squarespace. Squarespace leveled the playing field when it came to building websites. It’s a great piece of kit for anyone who wants to build a small portfolio website, a blog, a modest online store, etc. If you want a site, you want it done, and you want as little fuss as possible - have at it. Spend a couple of hours getting the look right - you don’t need to spin up servers, you don’t need to configure WordPress or install plugins. £10/month, job done. It’s fantastic - and I say that as someone who makes money doing the same thing that you can pay Squarespace to do. Except I don’t - and that’s the point. Squarespace isn’t going to help you if you need a completely stand-out website. It’s not the right tool for you if you want a bespoke CMS for your publication. It’s going to struggle if you need a high-traffic, multi-seller, international e-commerce platform. You can’t use it if you have specific data security requirements. Squarespace isn’t designed to help in those cases. In those scenarios, and hundreds more, you need a web developer. (Hello, by the way! 👋) Generative AI is like Squarespace - a great tool for a simple and specific need. I don’t believe I’ve lost significant business because Squarespace exists. I also think that thousands more people have an accessible online voice because of the likes of Squarespace, people who wouldn’t have been able to have one without it. In the same vein, I don’t believe this wave of AI will result in millions of 9-5 “office worker” jobs lost. There are things it just isn’t designed to do. There was a period where we all got caught up in the hype that AI would solve everything, and we’d be able to kick back in our utopia while the robots did all the work. Maybe that’s coming, but not yet. Not soon. And that’s OK - technology isn’t really supposed to be a broad-brush solution to all problems. Specific interventions need to be specifically deployed to get the best out of it. That’s where I believe we’re at. We are going to see an exponential rise in the number of people using Generative AI, in a much smaller number of use cases. I think that’s going to be really exciting. The low-hanging fruit, the easy return on investment stuff, will be more widely used. It’s will really open up how people can spend their time - not just physical hours, but also the mental capacity to think about more important things. Final thoughts It’s quite the rosy picture I’ve painted! Don’t misunderstand me, I know there are still hurdles to jump. There are ethical considerations, climate change factors, and myriad data concerns surrounding AI that I’ve not explored here. In the coming weeks and months, I will break these down. Watch this space. I also know that there are likely to be cases of some jobs being replaced, despite my sunny optimism. But in the round, I think we’re less likely to see entire jobs being taken over by machines, and instead have individual people be “augmented” in specific ways, giving them back time and capacity. I work predominately in the charity and social sector. It’s a space where it’s common for any given person to be doing the work of four people. I’m excited for a world where it’s accessible - both in terms of price and ease of use - for people in the space to only do the work of three people. Maybe even only two. I jest (sort of). But it is a real possibility. Small organisations can’t afford to hire extra people, and AI isn’t able to replace existing ones. But, perhaps for the first time, we have a genuinely viable third option, where for a little extra money we might get a lot more out. It will help people redefine what their work is, and to spend their time doing more meaningful work. So that’s where I think we are. And I am excited.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/gen-ai-office-scene.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/gen-ai-office-scene.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">I’ve recently changed how I consume content</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/ive-recently-changed-how-i-consume-content/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I’ve recently changed how I consume content" /><published>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/ive-recently-changed-how-i-consume-content</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/ive-recently-changed-how-i-consume-content/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been doing a revamp of the way I consume data lately, and in the interest of sharing (and having more content to write) I thought I’d post it here.</p>

<p>This also coincided with me getting a new phone, and not reinstalling many of my ‘usual’ social media apps. I’ve realised how much of my time I spent on X - not just doom-scrolling (though there was plenty of that), but also as a source of news, and sometimes a place to store thoughts.</p>

<p>Anyway, here’s how I digitally organise my brain. Shout out to the two big apps in my life: <a href="https://omnivore.app/">Omnivore</a>, and <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>. They feature a lot in this post.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Technology exists to make things easier. If it isn’t doing that, then rethink what you’re using it for.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="the-funnel---where-i-get-my-content">The Funnel - where I get my content</h1>

<h2 id="mastodon">Mastodon</h2>

<p>Since I don’t really use Twitter/X anymore, I’ve joined the pilgrimage to Mastodon. I think I’m still a little way off where I was at peak Twitter, but that is mostly because I’m trying to compare 10 years of Twitter use with like 10 months on the Fediverse. That said I do get a good amount of use from it - particularly accounts like <a href="https://mastodon.world/@longreads">Longreads</a> or more tech-specific feeds.</p>

<p>I’ve talked a little before about the way that <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/articles/mastodon-vs-twitter/">Mastodon differs from Twitter</a>, but one of the benefits, for me at least, is that it I’ve found it very easy to curate a feed that is predominantly about technology. I struggle to remember what the early days of Twitter were like. But even before it devolved it was still quite a “broad” place. Good, in its own way, but perhaps less focused.</p>

<h2 id="rss-feeds-and-omnivore">RSS feeds and Omnivore</h2>

<p>I’ve had a tumultuous relationship with RSS over the years. Like many, for the last decade I lamented the loss of Google Reader. In it’s wake, I’ve tried a lot of options, from <a href="https://feedly.com/">Feedly</a> to <a href="https://about.flipboard.com/">Flipboard</a>. But for some reason they’ve never really stuck. I think because I would use the RSS reader as the place to read content, and then have a different app to make notes, and then a different one again to store things like highlights / favourite posts etc.</p>

<p>Enter <a href="https://omnivore.app/">Omnivore</a> - for me it’s the first actual “most in one” platform that I’ve used where I actually do the things it suggests in the platform. You can subscribe to RSS feeds and the platform will periodically pull those feeds into your inbox, sync them for offline viewing (if you’re on mobile), and also allow you to make highlights and annotations. You can also create email addresses to allow you to sign up to newsletters, and read those in the app, keeping your inbox free of that ever expanding filtered folder of unread emails.</p>

<p>But neither of those were what initially drew me to Omnivore. It was actually it’s function as a “read it later” platform that swung it for me. It’s clean, has the usual tagging functionality you’d expect, and even lets you highlight and annotate pages from the app. Most importantly for me though, the mobile app is fantastic, and the ability to sync and read longform content offline has been a game changer. Despite living in 2023, I still find myself in patches of no signal for considerable stretches of my commute. Omnivore makes it really easy to scroll the usual places for things to read, send them over to the platform, and then actually do the reading while I’ve got no signal.</p>

<p>It will also allow you to spit things out into other applications, which for me is great because of the next part of my thought pipeline…</p>

<h1 id="the-hub---where-it-all-lives">The hub - where it all lives</h1>

<h2 id="obsidian">Obsidian</h2>

<p>I’ve been back and forth with <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a> for a while. A mixture of not really having the rest of my pipeline sorted, and being entrenched in <a href="https://www.notion.so/">Notion</a> for so long, meant that despite conceptually loving it, Obsidian never really stuck for me.</p>

<p>Meanwhile I loved Notion. It works like my brain works, and it can be adapted to handle pretty much anything. You need a basic project management tool? Somewhere to send articles to read and annotate later? A place to track habits? Somewhere to draft blog posts? Notion can handle all of that easily.</p>

<p>But lately it’s been running really slowly for me - something that is a common criticism of the platform. For me also, I need it to work smoothly offline, and Notion just doesn’t. I find myself doing a lot of note-taking and reading on my phone. Notion, for all its many many perks, does not behave well for me when all I want to do is fire up an app and jot down some thoughts.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, Obsidian is an offline product. It offers the same experience across platforms - handy for someone who spends an equal amount of time across Windows, Linux, and Android. It also has a number of options for dealing with syncing across devices. I’ve opted to pay for Obsidian’s own sync function (about £80 for the year), but there are other community driven ways of dealing with this.</p>

<p>Speaking of the community, there are thousands of extensions you can download and use to enhance Obsidian. It takes the opposite approach to tools like Notion, and gives you a streamlined base that you can customise exactly how you want, rather than giving you the world and letting you decide which corners you want to live in.</p>

<p>Neither option is inherently better or worse. The fact that everything is immediately available to you in Notion in some ways makes it easier to discover what it can do. But part of my issue with it has been it’s speed, and it’s hard to look past that.</p>

<h1 id="what-ive-learned">What I’ve learned</h1>

<h2 id="being-offline-is-more-important-to-me-than-i-realised">Being offline is more important to me than I realised</h2>

<p>I should have known this, having <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/musings/this-might-be-the-last-time-you-hear-me-talk-about-my-chromebook/">oft lamented</a> the old-school Chromebooks with their very generous definition of working online. (Reader: they don’t.)</p>

<p>I’m not one to claim that I want to optimise every second of my day. But equally I have really noticed how much more on the ball with specific topics I’ve been since reworking my pipeline. I can use the time on my commute to read and reflect on things that are important to me, rather than just scrolling aimlessly through my socials.</p>

<p>It goes beyond just using my commute time better. There’s much less friction between me having a thought and writing it down - and specifically between me reading something and having a thought about it, and then writing that down. Omnivore even syncs my Kindle highlights for me, so I’m not confined to just ruminating on news stories.</p>

<h2 id="simpler-is-better-but-its-also-subjective">Simpler is better, but it’s also subjective</h2>

<p>I didn’t intend for this to be an advert for Omnivore and Obsidian, and these platforms definitely won’t be for everyone. But one of the main draws for me is Obsidian’s use of Markdown. As I’ve <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/musings/i-blog-in-markdown-now/">mentioned before</a>, I really like the format for writing, but might not be everyone’s cup of tea. That Markdown-first way of capturing content, combined with a flexible way of storing, sorting, and linking data, makes it really easy for me to use Obsidian as my complete personal library.</p>

<h1 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h1>

<p>In reality, I probably count have replaced all of the above with the following three takeaways:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Being more selective about the social media you consume makes it easier to give yourself the brain space to actually consume and reflect on it. Go figure…</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Technology isn’t always about fancy plugins and shiny features. Sometimes the best tech just gets out of your way and lets you do the thinking.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It feels like we’re constantly pushed towards cloud-based and online options for products - in part because it’s easier there to push the shiny new things that keep you interested in the platform. But offline is just as good for a lot of things - and better for some.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Or, to put it even more simply: Technology exists to make things easier. If it isn’t doing that, then rethink what you’re using it for.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinions" /><category term="obsidian" /><category term="omnivore" /><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been doing a revamp of the way I consume data lately, and in the interest of sharing (and having more content to write) I thought I’d post it here. This also coincided with me getting a new phone, and not reinstalling many of my ‘usual’ social media apps. I’ve realised how much of my time I spent on X - not just doom-scrolling (though there was plenty of that), but also as a source of news, and sometimes a place to store thoughts. Anyway, here’s how I digitally organise my brain. Shout out to the two big apps in my life: Omnivore, and Obsidian. They feature a lot in this post. Technology exists to make things easier. If it isn’t doing that, then rethink what you’re using it for. The Funnel - where I get my content Mastodon Since I don’t really use Twitter/X anymore, I’ve joined the pilgrimage to Mastodon. I think I’m still a little way off where I was at peak Twitter, but that is mostly because I’m trying to compare 10 years of Twitter use with like 10 months on the Fediverse. That said I do get a good amount of use from it - particularly accounts like Longreads or more tech-specific feeds. I’ve talked a little before about the way that Mastodon differs from Twitter, but one of the benefits, for me at least, is that it I’ve found it very easy to curate a feed that is predominantly about technology. I struggle to remember what the early days of Twitter were like. But even before it devolved it was still quite a “broad” place. Good, in its own way, but perhaps less focused. RSS feeds and Omnivore I’ve had a tumultuous relationship with RSS over the years. Like many, for the last decade I lamented the loss of Google Reader. In it’s wake, I’ve tried a lot of options, from Feedly to Flipboard. But for some reason they’ve never really stuck. I think because I would use the RSS reader as the place to read content, and then have a different app to make notes, and then a different one again to store things like highlights / favourite posts etc. Enter Omnivore - for me it’s the first actual “most in one” platform that I’ve used where I actually do the things it suggests in the platform. You can subscribe to RSS feeds and the platform will periodically pull those feeds into your inbox, sync them for offline viewing (if you’re on mobile), and also allow you to make highlights and annotations. You can also create email addresses to allow you to sign up to newsletters, and read those in the app, keeping your inbox free of that ever expanding filtered folder of unread emails. But neither of those were what initially drew me to Omnivore. It was actually it’s function as a “read it later” platform that swung it for me. It’s clean, has the usual tagging functionality you’d expect, and even lets you highlight and annotate pages from the app. Most importantly for me though, the mobile app is fantastic, and the ability to sync and read longform content offline has been a game changer. Despite living in 2023, I still find myself in patches of no signal for considerable stretches of my commute. Omnivore makes it really easy to scroll the usual places for things to read, send them over to the platform, and then actually do the reading while I’ve got no signal. It will also allow you to spit things out into other applications, which for me is great because of the next part of my thought pipeline… The hub - where it all lives Obsidian I’ve been back and forth with Obsidian for a while. A mixture of not really having the rest of my pipeline sorted, and being entrenched in Notion for so long, meant that despite conceptually loving it, Obsidian never really stuck for me. Meanwhile I loved Notion. It works like my brain works, and it can be adapted to handle pretty much anything. You need a basic project management tool? Somewhere to send articles to read and annotate later? A place to track habits? Somewhere to draft blog posts? Notion can handle all of that easily. But lately it’s been running really slowly for me - something that is a common criticism of the platform. For me also, I need it to work smoothly offline, and Notion just doesn’t. I find myself doing a lot of note-taking and reading on my phone. Notion, for all its many many perks, does not behave well for me when all I want to do is fire up an app and jot down some thoughts. Meanwhile, Obsidian is an offline product. It offers the same experience across platforms - handy for someone who spends an equal amount of time across Windows, Linux, and Android. It also has a number of options for dealing with syncing across devices. I’ve opted to pay for Obsidian’s own sync function (about £80 for the year), but there are other community driven ways of dealing with this. Speaking of the community, there are thousands of extensions you can download and use to enhance Obsidian. It takes the opposite approach to tools like Notion, and gives you a streamlined base that you can customise exactly how you want, rather than giving you the world and letting you decide which corners you want to live in. Neither option is inherently better or worse. The fact that everything is immediately available to you in Notion in some ways makes it easier to discover what it can do. But part of my issue with it has been it’s speed, and it’s hard to look past that. What I’ve learned Being offline is more important to me than I realised I should have known this, having oft lamented the old-school Chromebooks with their very generous definition of working online. (Reader: they don’t.) I’m not one to claim that I want to optimise every second of my day. But equally I have really noticed how much more on the ball with specific topics I’ve been since reworking my pipeline. I can use the time on my commute to read and reflect on things that are important to me, rather than just scrolling aimlessly through my socials. It goes beyond just using my commute time better. There’s much less friction between me having a thought and writing it down - and specifically between me reading something and having a thought about it, and then writing that down. Omnivore even syncs my Kindle highlights for me, so I’m not confined to just ruminating on news stories. Simpler is better, but it’s also subjective I didn’t intend for this to be an advert for Omnivore and Obsidian, and these platforms definitely won’t be for everyone. But one of the main draws for me is Obsidian’s use of Markdown. As I’ve mentioned before, I really like the format for writing, but might not be everyone’s cup of tea. That Markdown-first way of capturing content, combined with a flexible way of storing, sorting, and linking data, makes it really easy for me to use Obsidian as my complete personal library. Final Thoughts In reality, I probably count have replaced all of the above with the following three takeaways: Being more selective about the social media you consume makes it easier to give yourself the brain space to actually consume and reflect on it. Go figure… Technology isn’t always about fancy plugins and shiny features. Sometimes the best tech just gets out of your way and lets you do the thinking. It feels like we’re constantly pushed towards cloud-based and online options for products - in part because it’s easier there to push the shiny new things that keep you interested in the platform. But offline is just as good for a lot of things - and better for some. Or, to put it even more simply: Technology exists to make things easier. If it isn’t doing that, then rethink what you’re using it for.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/stuttgart-library-jpg.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/stuttgart-library-jpg.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Takeaways from the IT Leaders Summit</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/takeaways-from-the-it-leaders-summit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Takeaways from the IT Leaders Summit" /><published>2023-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/takeaways-from-the-it-leaders-summit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/takeaways-from-the-it-leaders-summit/"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I went to <a href="https://www.computing.co.uk/">Computing’s</a> <a href="https://event.computing.co.uk/itleaderssummit2023/en/page/home">IT Leaders Summit</a>. Amongst other things, we talked about managing IT Security, the rise of Generative Artificial Intelligence, and what’s going on with IT budgets. Here are some of the things I’ve taken away.</p>

<h1 id="it-spending-is-up">IT spending is up</h1>

<p>This is driven by the higher cost of essential tech, and increase in the need for IT spending, and the rising cost of SaaS (Software as a Service) and Cloud products. (If all of those sound like they mean the same thing, welcome to IT budgeting 101.)</p>

<p>In one of the opening talks of the Summit, Computing’s John Leonard went through results of a survey the publication had conducted across the IT sector. Of the respondents, 50% reported an increase in real terms in the money they spent on IT compared to last year. Of this increase, the largest rises went to cloud infrastructure. Some organisations had reported rises of as much as 4x inflation for their licenses. While that was certainly at the higher end, the likes of Microsoft, Google, and Salesforce have or will be raising their prices by an average of 14% compared to 2022.</p>

<p>While actual spending is up, these are on things that individual companies don’t really have much control over. If you don’t want to pay the increase in license fees for your Microsoft 365 accounts, your other alternative is… Well you don’t really have one. At least, not one that doesn’t come with it’s own large costs to migrate. What this means is that the budgets that IT professionals have to play with when it comes to the “extra stuff” is greatly diminished. Companies are concerned about upcoming fixed costs - like what happens when your current software stack goes End Of Life and you’re forced to upgrade.</p>

<h1 id="strong-cyber-security-is-more-important-than-ever">Strong cyber security is more important than ever</h1>

<p>Traditional IT security is based on a very simple concept: here is a list of known viruses, bad people, and nefarious software. If you see it, delete it. That’s worked well enough for a while. But these days the problems aren’t confined to virus and spam emails. Modern hackers can leverage “safe” software - genuine applications that you have on your device right now - and twist their purpose.</p>

<p>In a talk on Zero Trust Security Measures, <a href="https://www.threatlocker.com/">Threatlocker’s</a> Seamus Lennon gave the example of a company which had been a victim of a ransomware attach using an email client, Windows Powershell, and the popular 7zip application. Blocking any of these apps is functionally impossible. You can’t run a company without your email client, and your Windows laptop can’t run without Powershell.</p>

<p>You can sort of mitigate for this in a “traditional” office setup, because your IT admin can stick a fancy firewall at the gates of your office and monitor everything that comes in and out. Except very few companies post-pandemic still operate in a way that makes this a failsafe. “The biggest challenge to network security,” says Lennon, “is that there is no network.” With the boom in home offices, remote working, and the average person now blurring the lines between personal and professional use of their office laptop, keeping devices safe in a world where ransomware attackers can use legitimate applications to cause damage is a IT security nightmare.</p>

<h1 id="ai-is-complicated">AI is… complicated</h1>

<p>And I don’t mean technically. There are a lot of things I hadn’t considered about Artificial Intelligence. Did you know, for example, that the increase in access to AI makes people less likely to collaborate? Dan McMahon from <a href="https://www.hymans.co.uk/">Hymans Robertson</a> made this point in a panel discussion. With AI tools cutting down on the grunt work needed for any given task, organisations are able to go further alone that they used to. Some are taking this as a sign that they don’t need to collaborate - it is much easier now to strike out on your own. I’m left to wonder, though it would be very hard to objectively measure this, whether progress in certain fields has actually slowed as a result of technology?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>AI is likely to remain the plaything of the privileged.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>AI is also likely to stay the purview of the privileged. Payment models for things like ChatGPT mean that the “free” version is several iterations behind what the paid plans provide. That’s not exactly new as a technology costing model. But Huseyin Seker from <a href="https://www.bcu.ac.uk/">Birmingham City University</a> made the point that as these costing models mature, those with resources are more likely to exponentially benefit from the technological gains that Artificial Intelligence provides.</p>

<p>Taking this thought a step further, much of generative AI “learns” from itself. By which I mean the exchanges are used to help modify and improve the platform. With barriers to access excluding certain groups, does that also mean we are more likely to create self-perpetuating echo-chambers of certain opinions?</p>

<p>And, spoiler alert, we’re about to talk more about payment for IT services…</p>

<h1 id="non-invasive-tech-is-going-to-cost-you">Non-invasive tech is going to cost you</h1>

<p>Recently, Meta announced they were exploring offering a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2023/oct/03/facebook-instagram-charge-ad-free-eu-meta-mobile-desktop">paid tier for Instagram</a> for EU users. This paid tier would mean they were not subject to targetted adverts on the platform. This is part of a drive by the EU to end the era of “if the service is free, then you’re the product”. On the face of it, this isn’t a bad idea. The reason we can flick through Instagram reels “for free” is because the data of what we look at, like, and share is worth a lot of money to Meta. Offering a paid tier allows you to still consume user-generated content that you like, but without having your data mined and sold.</p>

<p>My concern is that we’re going to enter an age where the ability to consume content safe from algorithmic influence is only going to be for those who can afford it. In the same way that those benefiting from - and therefore influencing the direction of - AI. Here though, my concern is less about how the platforms will be shaped by those with money. It is more about what happens to those who won’t or can’t pay. They will still be served those ads, and the ads will be more aggressive for it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I talk a little more about how pervasive technology is in my blog about <a href="https://willrc.co.uk/musings/technology-and-the-cult-of-celebrity/">Technology and the Cult of Celebrity</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="most-people-will-experience-online-harm">Most people will experience online harm</h2>

<p>Did you know that 62% of adults who access the internet have encountered online harm in the last week? Did you know that number goes up to 68% for 13-17 year olds? Chloe Colliver of <a href="https://www.ofcom.org.uk/home">Ofcom</a>, talked through some of the research that lead to the creation of the Online Safety Bill - due to be passed into law in the coming weeks.</p>

<p>The average person in the UK spends a little over 4 hours online every day, and of that nearly an hour is spent just on Meta apps and websites (Facebook, Instagram, WhatsApp, and Messenger). Other social media platforms, including Snap, X, and TikTok, also make up considerable amounts of time - especially for younger users. The Online Safety Bill is designed to protect UK Citizens from online harm, including illegal pornography, online trolling and other forms of verbal abuse, and certain types of internet fraud.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There are a number of legitimate reasons why someone might need to be anonymous online.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While a full discussion on the Bill is beyond the scope of this post, there are some things to note. It’s a very complicated document that can be interpreted in a number of ways - something that critics have been eager to point out. It also seems to demand the ability to decrypt secure messages, and calls into question how anonymous one can be on the internet. Clearly there are nefarious purposes for being untraceable online, but also there are a great many reasons someone might <em>need</em> to remain anonymous (tangentially related: <a href="https://anonyome.com/2021/04/removing-anonymity-online-would-risk-the-most-vulnerable-users/">this 2021 post from Anonyome Labs</a> about the risk of removing online anonymity).</p>

<p>That said, you can’t argue with the numbers. With more young people accessing the internet more often, at a younger age, there certainly needs to be more thought put into making sure people are safe. As pricing models for everything from Generative AI to messaging apps evolve, different groups are going to be targeted for different reasons.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Check out the <a href="https://counterhate.com/">Centre for Countering Digital Hate</a>, which (alongside being sued by Elon Musk) is celebrating its 4th anniversary.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h1>

<p>I continue to be a technology optimist. The benefits we can all get from advances are almost limitless. But it is just as important to remain aware of how fast moving tech can also be something to keep an eye on. We are continually putting more of ourselves online, conducting more of our business globally, and becoming more reliant on third parties to ensure our day-to-day lives run smoothly. There isn’t necessarily anything wrong with that, but make sure you keep yourself up-to-date.</p>

<p><strong><em>If you want to chat about anything you’ve read here, do feel free to reach out to me on <a href="mailto:will@willrc.co.uk">email</a>, or via <a href="https://twitter.com/willranjhill">X (formerly know as Twitter)</a>, <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@willrc">Mastodon</a>, or <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/willranjanchurchill/">LinkedIn</a>.</em></strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinions" /><category term="ai" /><category term="chatgpt" /><category term="cyber-security" /><category term="it-budgeting" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last week I went to Computing’s IT Leaders Summit. Amongst other things, we talked about managing IT Security, the rise of Generative Artificial Intelligence, and what’s going on with IT budgets. Here are some of the things I’ve taken away. IT spending is up This is driven by the higher cost of essential tech, and increase in the need for IT spending, and the rising cost of SaaS (Software as a Service) and Cloud products. (If all of those sound like they mean the same thing, welcome to IT budgeting 101.) In one of the opening talks of the Summit, Computing’s John Leonard went through results of a survey the publication had conducted across the IT sector. Of the respondents, 50% reported an increase in real terms in the money they spent on IT compared to last year. Of this increase, the largest rises went to cloud infrastructure. Some organisations had reported rises of as much as 4x inflation for their licenses. While that was certainly at the higher end, the likes of Microsoft, Google, and Salesforce have or will be raising their prices by an average of 14% compared to 2022. While actual spending is up, these are on things that individual companies don’t really have much control over. If you don’t want to pay the increase in license fees for your Microsoft 365 accounts, your other alternative is… Well you don’t really have one. At least, not one that doesn’t come with it’s own large costs to migrate. What this means is that the budgets that IT professionals have to play with when it comes to the “extra stuff” is greatly diminished. Companies are concerned about upcoming fixed costs - like what happens when your current software stack goes End Of Life and you’re forced to upgrade. Strong cyber security is more important than ever Traditional IT security is based on a very simple concept: here is a list of known viruses, bad people, and nefarious software. If you see it, delete it. That’s worked well enough for a while. But these days the problems aren’t confined to virus and spam emails. Modern hackers can leverage “safe” software - genuine applications that you have on your device right now - and twist their purpose. In a talk on Zero Trust Security Measures, Threatlocker’s Seamus Lennon gave the example of a company which had been a victim of a ransomware attach using an email client, Windows Powershell, and the popular 7zip application. Blocking any of these apps is functionally impossible. You can’t run a company without your email client, and your Windows laptop can’t run without Powershell. You can sort of mitigate for this in a “traditional” office setup, because your IT admin can stick a fancy firewall at the gates of your office and monitor everything that comes in and out. Except very few companies post-pandemic still operate in a way that makes this a failsafe. “The biggest challenge to network security,” says Lennon, “is that there is no network.” With the boom in home offices, remote working, and the average person now blurring the lines between personal and professional use of their office laptop, keeping devices safe in a world where ransomware attackers can use legitimate applications to cause damage is a IT security nightmare. AI is… complicated And I don’t mean technically. There are a lot of things I hadn’t considered about Artificial Intelligence. Did you know, for example, that the increase in access to AI makes people less likely to collaborate? Dan McMahon from Hymans Robertson made this point in a panel discussion. With AI tools cutting down on the grunt work needed for any given task, organisations are able to go further alone that they used to. Some are taking this as a sign that they don’t need to collaborate - it is much easier now to strike out on your own. I’m left to wonder, though it would be very hard to objectively measure this, whether progress in certain fields has actually slowed as a result of technology? AI is likely to remain the plaything of the privileged. AI is also likely to stay the purview of the privileged. Payment models for things like ChatGPT mean that the “free” version is several iterations behind what the paid plans provide. That’s not exactly new as a technology costing model. But Huseyin Seker from Birmingham City University made the point that as these costing models mature, those with resources are more likely to exponentially benefit from the technological gains that Artificial Intelligence provides. Taking this thought a step further, much of generative AI “learns” from itself. By which I mean the exchanges are used to help modify and improve the platform. With barriers to access excluding certain groups, does that also mean we are more likely to create self-perpetuating echo-chambers of certain opinions? And, spoiler alert, we’re about to talk more about payment for IT services… Non-invasive tech is going to cost you Recently, Meta announced they were exploring offering a paid tier for Instagram for EU users. This paid tier would mean they were not subject to targetted adverts on the platform. This is part of a drive by the EU to end the era of “if the service is free, then you’re the product”. On the face of it, this isn’t a bad idea. The reason we can flick through Instagram reels “for free” is because the data of what we look at, like, and share is worth a lot of money to Meta. Offering a paid tier allows you to still consume user-generated content that you like, but without having your data mined and sold. My concern is that we’re going to enter an age where the ability to consume content safe from algorithmic influence is only going to be for those who can afford it. In the same way that those benefiting from - and therefore influencing the direction of - AI. Here though, my concern is less about how the platforms will be shaped by those with money. It is more about what happens to those who won’t or can’t pay. They will still be served those ads, and the ads will be more aggressive for it. I talk a little more about how pervasive technology is in my blog about Technology and the Cult of Celebrity Most people will experience online harm Did you know that 62% of adults who access the internet have encountered online harm in the last week? Did you know that number goes up to 68% for 13-17 year olds? Chloe Colliver of Ofcom, talked through some of the research that lead to the creation of the Online Safety Bill - due to be passed into law in the coming weeks. The average person in the UK spends a little over 4 hours online every day, and of that nearly an hour is spent just on Meta apps and websites (Facebook, Instagram, WhatsApp, and Messenger). Other social media platforms, including Snap, X, and TikTok, also make up considerable amounts of time - especially for younger users. The Online Safety Bill is designed to protect UK Citizens from online harm, including illegal pornography, online trolling and other forms of verbal abuse, and certain types of internet fraud. There are a number of legitimate reasons why someone might need to be anonymous online. While a full discussion on the Bill is beyond the scope of this post, there are some things to note. It’s a very complicated document that can be interpreted in a number of ways - something that critics have been eager to point out. It also seems to demand the ability to decrypt secure messages, and calls into question how anonymous one can be on the internet. Clearly there are nefarious purposes for being untraceable online, but also there are a great many reasons someone might need to remain anonymous (tangentially related: this 2021 post from Anonyome Labs about the risk of removing online anonymity). That said, you can’t argue with the numbers. With more young people accessing the internet more often, at a younger age, there certainly needs to be more thought put into making sure people are safe. As pricing models for everything from Generative AI to messaging apps evolve, different groups are going to be targeted for different reasons. Check out the Centre for Countering Digital Hate, which (alongside being sued by Elon Musk) is celebrating its 4th anniversary. Final thoughts I continue to be a technology optimist. The benefits we can all get from advances are almost limitless. But it is just as important to remain aware of how fast moving tech can also be something to keep an eye on. We are continually putting more of ourselves online, conducting more of our business globally, and becoming more reliant on third parties to ensure our day-to-day lives run smoothly. There isn’t necessarily anything wrong with that, but make sure you keep yourself up-to-date. If you want to chat about anything you’ve read here, do feel free to reach out to me on email, or via X (formerly know as Twitter), Mastodon, or LinkedIn.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/laptop-jpg.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/laptop-jpg.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>